<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>English orthography. Or The art of writing and spelling true English in three parts ... By John Chalmer, teacher of the arts of writing and accounts, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Chalmers, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612056</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2785:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>English orthography. Or The art of writing and spelling true English in three parts ... By John Chalmer, teacher of the arts of writing and accounts, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Chalmers, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh at the Golden Ball, against the Royal Exchange in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>Lacks pages 77-78.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Aberdeen University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English language --  Orthography and spelling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Letter-writing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:1"/>
            <p>Engliſh Orthography: OR, The Art of WRITING AND <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ELLING True ENGLISH, In Three PARTS.</p>
            <p>PART I. Contains all what is neceſſary for the Letters in Orthography, and every Letter conſidered in particular.</p>
            <p>PART II. Contains the Spelling part, with Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for Reading, Spelling and Underſtanding all hard Words, with the Abbreviations in Letters and Figures; alſo plain and eaſie Rules to underſtand the Stops or Pauſes, and an Example on every one with all Marks and Directions.</p>
            <p>Together with a Table of the moſt material Words that are ſpelt differently and ſounded alike, very neceſſary to be known, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thoſe who have not learn'd the Grammar may learn to ſpell True Engliſh.</p>
            <p>PART III. Preſents the Learner with ample and uſefull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions how to write Letters of all Sorts, and to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Perſons, and the Titles of Honour and Reſpects due to all Ranks, with Beginnings and Concluſions on many Occaſions.</p>
            <p>Alſo uſual Precedents for Common Affairs, very neceſſary for Perſons of all Ranks.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN CHALMER,</hi> Teacher of the Art of Writing and Accounts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ingenium niſi ſit ſtudium flos eſt ſine fructu</l>
               <l>Haec duo conjuncta, fructificare ſolent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball,</hi> againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Royal Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179339:2"/>
            <head>Engliſh Orthography, Containing The <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Writing</hi> Right And <hi>Spelling</hi> Well: With <hi>Directions</hi> for <hi>Reading Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Letters</hi> to Perſons of all Qualities. Very <hi>neceſſary</hi> for <hi>young Perſons</hi> both <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> eſpecially thoſe who have not learned the Grammar. PART I.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ORthography</hi> is the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Writing</hi> Right and <hi>Spelling</hi> Well. This <hi>conſiſts</hi> in placing the <hi>true</hi> Letters and <hi>proper</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, appertaining to every <hi>word,</hi> in their <hi>due</hi> and <hi>rightful order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> thing, therefore, to be conſidered, will be the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> or <hi>Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Letter</hi> is the <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> part of a <hi>word</hi> that can be <hi>written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Engliſh</hi> there are twenty ſix Letters.</p>
               <p>a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r ſ t v u w x y z.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179339:3"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe</hi> following are the ſeveral <hi>Phaenomena</hi> or <hi>appearances</hi> of Characters amongſt us.</p>
               <p>The great Engliſh Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T V X Y Z.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſmall Engliſh Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r ſ t v u w x y z.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great Roman Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A B C D E F G H I J K L M N O P Q R S T V U W X Y Z.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſmall Roman Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r ſ t v u w x y z.</p>
               <p>The great Italian Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A B C D E F G H I J K L M N O P Q R S T V <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> W X Y Z.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſmall Italian Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r ſ t v u w x y z.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179339:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Diphthongs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Letters</hi> are divided into <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Conſonants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Vowels</hi> are <hi>a, e, i, o, u</hi> and <hi>y Greek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Vowel</hi> maketh a <hi>perfect ſound</hi> of it ſelf, without a <hi>Conſonant;</hi> as <hi>a man, e-very, i-dolatry, ô Lord, u-biquity, y-cleped:</hi> But this <hi>laſt</hi> ſort of <hi>words</hi> are now almoſt <hi>obſolete</hi> and <hi>out</hi> of <hi>uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two</hi> Vowels <hi>conjoyned</hi> together make a <hi>Diphthong,</hi> which is either <hi>Proper</hi> or <hi>Improper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proper</hi> Diphthongs are <hi>two</hi> Vowels <hi>written</hi> and <hi>ſounded</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being 8 in number: <hi>ai, ei, oi au, eu, ou, ee, oo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when 2 <hi>Vowels</hi> meet together, and but <hi>one</hi> of them is <hi>ſounded,</hi> they are accounted <hi>Improper</hi> Diphthongs, and commonly <hi>reckoned</hi> 6, <hi>ay, ey, oy, aw, ew, ow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Proper</hi> ones occur in the <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>middle</hi> of words: as <hi>aim, either, oiſter, author, feud, found, bleed, book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when the <hi>ſame</hi> ſound waits upon the <hi>end</hi> of a word, then they become <hi>Improper</hi> Diphthongs; as, <hi>pray, prey, imploy, draw, few, plow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Au, eu,</hi> and <hi>ou</hi> are ſounded like <hi>aw, ew, ow,</hi> and ordinarily <hi>appear</hi> in the <hi>front</hi> and <hi>middle</hi> of words: but <hi>ſometimes,</hi> when the <hi>ſound</hi> is <hi>flattiſh,</hi> then the <hi>Improper</hi> muſt be uſed; as, <hi>award, ewer, own,</hi> or <hi>Drawer, Brewer, Flower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes 3 Vowels come <hi>crowding</hi> together, and muſt be pronounced, as <hi>eau</hi> in <hi>Beauty, ieu</hi> in <hi>lieu [i. e.</hi> Place, a <hi>French</hi> word] <hi>uai</hi> in <hi>acquaint, uee</hi> in <hi>Queen.</hi> Theſe and the <hi>like,</hi> are by <hi>ſome</hi> ſtiled <hi>Tripthongs,</hi> which not being of any <hi>conſiderable uſe,</hi> are not <hi>much</hi> taken <hi>notice</hi> of.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>But the <hi>Young Tyro,</hi> who <hi>begins</hi> to <hi>read,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is not <hi>concern'd</hi> ſuch <hi>niceties</hi> to heed:</l>
                  <l>Though when more <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> do command,</l>
                  <l>Then it is <hi>fit</hi> ſuch things to <hi>underſtand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:179339:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of <hi>Conſonants.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COnſonants</hi> are Letters, which of <hi>themſelves</hi> can make <hi>no ſound,</hi> without the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of a <hi>vowel;</hi> they are in number 20.</p>
               <p>b, c, d, f, g, h, j, k, l, m, n, p, q, r, ſ, t, v, w, x, z.</p>
               <p>Amongſt <hi>theſe,</hi> 8 are <hi>Mutes,</hi> or <hi>dumb</hi> Letters, which make <hi>no</hi> ſound of themſelves, but require the <hi>Letter</hi> [e] at the <hi>end,</hi> to <hi>help</hi> them out.</p>
               <p>b, c, d, g, k, p, q, t.</p>
               <p>There are, likewiſe, 8 which we may term <hi>ſemi-vowels,</hi> or half Vowels, becauſe they <hi>commence</hi> their <hi>ſound</hi> with the <hi>vowel</hi> [e] and <hi>terminate</hi> in <hi>themſelves:</hi> viz, j, f, l, m, n, r, ſ, x.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Five</hi> are Liquids, becauſe they <hi>loſe</hi> their <hi>force</hi> and <hi>efficacy:</hi> as l, m, n, r, ſ.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>ſound</hi> of any word reſteth upon a <hi>Conſonant</hi> in the <hi>beginning, middle,</hi> or <hi>ending</hi> of a word, then the <hi>Conſonant</hi> muſt be writ <hi>double:</hi> as <hi>addition, common, contract,</hi> and the <hi>like</hi> words, very <hi>frequent</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingenious</hi> Youths the <hi>myſtery</hi> will <hi>find,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If once they <hi>fix</hi> the <hi>notion</hi> in their <hi>mind:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by their little <hi>doubtings</hi> will unſcrew,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>More</hi> than their <hi>Maſters</hi> either <hi>taught</hi> or <hi>knew.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the <hi>Letters,</hi> in order.</head>
               <p>TO <hi>ſpeak</hi> or <hi>write</hi> exactly, is a work, which requireth much <hi>time,</hi> and much <hi>care</hi> and <hi>application;</hi> wherefore, that you may <hi>ſurmount</hi> all <hi>difficulties</hi> and hardſhips of <hi>Orthography,</hi> I judge it <hi>expedient</hi> to conſider the <hi>force</hi> and <hi>propriety</hi> of <hi>every</hi> Letter in the <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>habet,</hi> by it ſelf.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:4"/>
               <p>Many <hi>words</hi> have certain <hi>Letters</hi> in them that are <hi>not ſounded,</hi> and <hi>others</hi> which have not their <hi>proper</hi> ſound; and ſome <hi>laſtly,</hi> that are <hi>indued</hi> with the <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>an other,</hi> which of neceſſity muſt create a <hi>mighty impediment</hi> to the <hi>Candidates</hi> of our <hi>Tongue,</hi> both in <hi>pronunciation</hi> and <hi>ſpelling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A is ſounded <hi>flat</hi> before a <hi>double Conſonant,</hi> as <hi>all, attract.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes it <hi>loſeth</hi> its <hi>ſound,</hi> as in <hi>Iſaac, Aaron, Pharaoh, Balaam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>B is not pronounc'd in <hi>Lamb, doubt, thumb, dumb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>C hath <hi>two</hi> ſounds, that of [k] and that of [ſ.] When it comes <hi>before a, o, oo, u</hi> it <hi>imitates</hi> the ſound of [k] as <hi>Cat, Comb, Cook, Cuſtom:</hi> but when it <hi>precedes e, i, y</hi> or <hi>ee,</hi> it ſounds like [<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>] as <hi>Cell, Cider, Cypreſs, exceed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ch</hi> in all words of a <hi>purely Engliſh</hi> ſtamp, hath a <hi>peculiar</hi> ſound both <hi>before</hi> and <hi>after</hi> a Vowel, as <hi>change, Cheapſide, Checquer, Church,</hi> and after a vowel, as <hi>reach, preach, much.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in a word of <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Greek</hi> Origination [ch] emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the ſound of [k] as in <hi>Chileab, Nebuchadnezzar, Malchus, Lyſimachus, Eunuch, Stomach, Architect:</hi> except ſome <hi>few</hi> words, as <hi>Rachel, Cherubim,</hi> and where a <hi>conſonant</hi> follows, as <hi>Arch-biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>C coming betwixt a <hi>vowel</hi> and [k] is <hi>not</hi> pronounced, but onely <hi>fortifies</hi> the ſound of [k] as <hi>ſack, mock, ſtock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo when it is written <hi>after</hi> ſ, it has nothing to <hi>do</hi> with its own <hi>peculiar</hi> pronunciation in <hi>Conſcience, Diſciple</hi> and ſuch as derive from the <hi>Latine:</hi> it onely makes the [ſ] ſomewhat <hi>ſharper</hi> than ordinary.</p>
               <p>D is not ſounded in <hi>Bridge, Priviledge, Pledge</hi> and ſuch <hi>like;</hi> but yet it <hi>ſeems</hi> to <hi>give</hi> a <hi>vigour</hi> to the <hi>pronunciation</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>E is <hi>often</hi> written, but <hi>not</hi> pronounc'd at the <hi>end</hi> of a word, as <hi>vertue, houſe, fire, frame:</hi> but it is <hi>otherwiſe</hi> in words of more immediate <hi>foreign</hi> derivation; as <hi>Epitome, Conge, Jeſſe, Jubile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When it is plac'd at the <hi>end,</hi> it ſerves onely to <hi>lengthen</hi> the <hi>word,</hi> and is never <hi>pronounced</hi> at the <hi>end</hi> of a word <hi>truly Engliſh</hi> but in theſe <hi>Monoſyllables me, he, we, be,</hi> and the like: For it hath <hi>no ſound</hi> in a word of 2 <hi>Syllables.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>E ſhould never come after <hi>[ſs]</hi> at the <hi>end</hi> of a word; I know it is not ſeldom <hi>written</hi> and <hi>printed</hi> otherwiſe: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>taken</hi> away from <hi>ſome</hi> words, it quite <hi>alters</hi> the ſenſe, as <hi>fire, made, fare;</hi> leave out the [e's] and the <hi>ſenſe</hi> is altogether <hi>loſt,</hi> as <hi>fir, mad, far.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:5"/>
               <p>In <hi>many</hi> words [e] gives a <hi>ſoftning</hi> reliſh to the <hi>ſound,</hi> and prolongs the <hi>tone</hi> of them, as <hi>price, force, Grace, age, Stage,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When a word <hi>ends</hi> with a <hi>double</hi> Conſonant it is <hi>needleſs</hi> to put [e] after it, as <hi>conteſt, hall, conſtruct,</hi> &amp;c. In <hi>former</hi> times we find, they were ſo <hi>enamour'd</hi> with <hi>this</hi> Letter, that they generally brought up the <hi>rear</hi> of <hi>every</hi> word with it that could any ways <hi>bear</hi> it; and ſome indifferent Heads either through <hi>inadvertency</hi> or <hi>obſtinate ignorance</hi> carry on the <hi>humour</hi> ſtill, which to the <hi>underſtanding</hi> readers is ſufficiently <hi>ridiculous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>F keeps its own natural force in all words and never loſeth its ſound.</p>
               <p>G hath <hi>two</hi> ſounds, one <hi>hard,</hi> as in <hi>Gold, Guide, Ghoſt,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſharp,</hi> as in <hi>George, General; both</hi> which ſounds are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>found</hi> in <hi>one</hi> word, as in <hi>ſuggeſt, exaggerate.</hi> But if <hi>a, o,</hi> or <hi>u</hi> follow the <hi>later</hi> ſound, the <hi>word</hi> muſt not be <hi>written</hi> with [G] but with [J] conſonant, as <hi>James, Joſeph, Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo <hi>ſilent</hi> in <hi>many</hi> words, as in <hi>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gm, ſign, Sovereign, foreign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[gh] is ſounded like [ff] in <hi>laugh, cough, enough,</hi> without any <hi>reaſon</hi> but onely what may be <hi>deduced</hi> from <hi>vulgar</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. Some imagine, it is, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cannot <hi>gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> it nor <hi>pronounce</hi> any thing through the <hi>throat,</hi> with whom I ſo <hi>far</hi> agree as to <hi>think,</hi> that moſt of them take no <hi>delight</hi> to do ſo.</p>
               <p>In <hi>other</hi> words it is <hi>not</hi> at all pronounced; as in <hi>might, ſtraight, weight, right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>H the <hi>Romans</hi> by no means <hi>admit</hi> to be a <hi>Letter,</hi> and the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> reject it, for that they have no <hi>Character,</hi> but onely a <hi>poor point</hi> for it. But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have very <hi>kindly</hi> beſtow'd a <hi>Character</hi> upon it, ſo that it is <hi>allowed</hi> to be a <hi>member</hi> of the <hi>family</hi> of <hi>Letters</hi> in general: But why it ſhould not be ſo in <hi>particular,</hi> I ſhall not ſtay here to <hi>determine,</hi> but leave it to <hi>another</hi> opportunity.</p>
               <p>I is <hi>rarely</hi> pronounced in <hi>ſuch</hi> words as <hi>Chriſtopher, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Rhetorick, Rheum;</hi> and at the <hi>end</hi> of all <hi>Hebrew</hi> words it is <hi>loſt,</hi> as <hi>Shiloah, Sarah, Jeremiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I <hi>Vowel</hi> is not ſounded in <hi>Parliament, faſhion</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>J <hi>Conſonant,</hi> which I will <hi>take leave</hi> to <hi>ſtyle</hi> by the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>[jod]</hi> when <hi>ſituated</hi> before a <hi>Vowel</hi> is ſounded as <hi>g,</hi> and muſt be written <hi>different</hi> from an [i] <hi>vowel,</hi> as in <hi>juſt, judge,</hi> with a long <hi>trole</hi> at the <hi>bottom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I add <hi>[jod]</hi> and <hi>[vau]</hi> (for ſo I have preſumed to call <hi>[v]</hi>) to the 24 Letters, as two <hi>diſtinct</hi> and <hi>ſeparate</hi> Letters,
<pb facs="tcp:179339:5"/> having as great <hi>diſcrimination</hi> from <hi>[i]</hi> and <hi>[u]</hi> both in <hi>form, nature</hi> and <hi>ſound,</hi> as any of the <hi>other</hi> Letters have from <hi>one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>K is never <hi>doubled</hi> in any <hi>Engliſh</hi> word, but has the <hi>addition</hi> of C to fortify its <hi>pronunciation,</hi> as <hi>black, Clock;</hi> though in words of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Idiom and <hi>off-ſpring</hi> it may be <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> as in <hi>Habbakkuk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>K is <hi>needleſs,</hi> and may be indifferently <hi>left</hi> out or <hi>put</hi> in at the <hi>end</hi> of all words <hi>derived</hi> from the <hi>Latine,</hi> as in theſe words <hi>public, Phyſic, Arithmetic,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>L is omitted in <hi>many</hi> words, as <hi>half, calf, calm, Salve, Salmon, Faulcon:</hi> Yet this happens according to the <hi>Gentileneſs</hi> of the <hi>mouth</hi> that pronounceth it.</p>
               <p>L is <hi>doubled</hi> at the <hi>end</hi> of all words of <hi>one Syllable,</hi> as <hi>Hall, ſmall, call, fill, kill,</hi> unleſs the Monoſyllable have a <hi>diphthong,</hi> then it terminates with a <hi>ſingle</hi> [l] as <hi>hail, pail, fail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All</hi> words exceeding one <hi>Syllable</hi> which <hi>end</hi> in [i] ſhould <hi>conclude</hi> with a <hi>ſingle</hi> [l] although many <hi>Scholars</hi> take little <hi>notice</hi> of it in <hi>writing,</hi> as <hi>ſubſtantial, Cathedral, General, real, continual, immortal,</hi> except when the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>ſound</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the <hi>laſt</hi> letter; as <hi>rebell, compell, repell, deſtill,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>M is never <hi>left</hi> out of any <hi>word,</hi> and is always <hi>unchangeable</hi> in its <hi>ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>N is not pronounced in <hi>ſolemn, hymn, Autumn, condemn,</hi> words of <hi>Latin</hi> Extraction.</p>
               <p>O miſſeth its ſound in many words, as <hi>Youth, courage, People, jeopardy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[oo] is ſounded like <hi>woo,</hi> as in <hi>chooſe, roof,</hi> nevertheleſs it ſounds a <hi>ſhort</hi> [u] in <hi>good, blood, ſtood, hood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P is not pronounced in <hi>Pſalm, contempt, ſumptuous, ſymptom,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ph</hi> hath the ſound of [f] in <hi>many</hi> words, as <hi>Philip, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, Theophilus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q is never written without [u] <hi>vowel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R is no-where <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> but is evermore <hi>expreſt</hi> where it is <hi>written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S loſeth its ſound in <hi>Viſcount, Iſland.</hi> It is ſounded like [z] in <hi>many</hi> words, as <hi>peaſe, buſie, praiſe, raiſe,</hi> which may be <hi>aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed</hi> to the <hi>vicinity</hi> and <hi>neighbourhood</hi> of the <hi>vowels</hi> and <hi>dihp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thongs,</hi> cauſing the <hi>Tongue</hi> to <hi>dwell</hi> the longer on the <hi>conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ti muſt be pronounced like [ſi] always <hi>before</hi> a vowel, as <hi>frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrition:</hi> but if no vowel <hi>follow,</hi> then it muſt be <hi>ſound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:6"/> as it is <hi>written.</hi> However; if [ſ] come before [ti] then it is <hi>pronounced,</hi> as it lieth <hi>naturally</hi> in the word, as <hi>queſtion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>V <hi>conſonant</hi> [or vau] differs very <hi>much</hi> from [u] <hi>vowel,</hi> and from [w] and ought to be <hi>regarded</hi> with a very <hi>carefull</hi> eye, ſeeing it is a <hi>grand errour</hi> to write [u] <hi>vowel</hi> for [v] <hi>conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> as <hi>many</hi> do in ſuch words, as <hi>love, vain, Vulture, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,</hi> which look <hi>diſmally</hi> altogether in <hi>vowels</hi> thus, <hi>loue, uain, uulture,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>U <hi>vowel</hi> is <hi>omitted</hi> in the <hi>pronunciation</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> words, <hi>guard, gueſt, guide,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>W is ſeldom ſounded <hi>after</hi> [o] or <hi>before</hi> [r] as <hi>ſhallow, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, widow, write, wrath, wrangle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>X never begins any word without an [e] before it, except <hi>proper</hi> names, as <hi>Xerxes, Xenophon, Xeno.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Y is put commonly at the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>many</hi> words for [ie] although [ie] is the <hi>better,</hi> and moſt <hi>natural</hi> way, which I ſhall not here <hi>diſpute,</hi> but <hi>leave</hi> every man to his <hi>own judgment</hi> or <hi>caprice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Y is never written in the <hi>middle</hi> of any word that is <hi>truly Engliſh:</hi> but we <hi>often</hi>-times meet with it in words <hi>borrowed</hi> from the <hi>extraneous</hi> and <hi>dead</hi> Languages, as <hi>Apocrypha, Gymno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Z is very <hi>rarely</hi> uſed in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> becauſe [s] has the <hi>ſame</hi> ſound in <hi>many</hi> words.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bleſt</hi> be the <hi>man,</hi> who <hi>Letters</hi> firſt did find,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>bleſs</hi> with nice <hi>Inſtructions</hi> all <hi>Mankind:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Surely the <hi>Heavenly Powers</hi> inſpir'd his <hi>mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>ſlight</hi> ſuch <hi>Sacred Gifts</hi> we ſhould be <hi>ſorry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whence we draw <hi>Prophane</hi> and <hi>Sacred</hi> Story:</l>
                  <l>Let us be <hi>thankful,</hi> and give <hi>God</hi> the <hi>glory.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of <hi>Capitals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Capital</hi> Letters are of <hi>great</hi> uſe (though extremely <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected</hi>) as being <hi>proper</hi> on <hi>many</hi> occaſions, eſpecially theſe <hi>following.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In the <hi>beginning</hi> of all <hi>Writings, Paragraphs</hi> and <hi>Periods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>firſt</hi> Letter of all <hi>Proper Names, Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Sirnames,</hi> and <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>all</hi> ſorts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Names of <hi>Arts, Sciences, Dignities, Offices, Trades</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. All remarkable <hi>Paſſages</hi> and <hi>Sentences</hi> are uſually <hi>written</hi> in great <hi>Capitals,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19. <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OF NAZARETH.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>Perſonal</hi> Pronoun [I] muſt be always a <hi>great</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When we write to <hi>great</hi> and illuſtrious <hi>Perſonages,</hi> and <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate</hi> them either by <hi>noun</hi> or <hi>pronoun,</hi> we are to uſe Capitals, as,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>We will and command you,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Our will and pleaſure is,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Your <hi>Grace's Petitioner,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Your <hi>Lo. commanded me,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>You <hi>are to appear before <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. In things <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Divine:</hi> we ſhould take <hi>care</hi> always to write <hi>[God]</hi> with a <hi>great</hi> Letter to demonſtrate the <hi>great aw</hi> we have of him, and the great <hi>deference</hi> and <hi>veneration</hi> we pay him.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And laſtly, every <hi>Line</hi> in <hi>Poetry</hi> muſt begin with a <hi>great Letter,</hi> as in the <hi>enſuing</hi> verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thou take <hi>pains</hi> in what is <hi>good,</hi> the pains</l>
                  <l>Doth quickly <hi>vaniſh,</hi> but the good <hi>remains.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou take <hi>pleaſure</hi> in a <hi>naughtie</hi> thing,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ill</hi> remains; the <hi>pleaſure</hi> pains doth bring.</l>
                  <l>What <hi>worſe</hi> art thou for <hi>pains,</hi> when <hi>gon</hi> at laſt,</l>
                  <l>Or what availeth <hi>pleaſure,</hi> when it's <hi>paſt?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of <hi>abbreviations</hi> in <hi>Capitals</hi> and <hi>other</hi> Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Romans</hi> uſed to make two, three, or more <hi>Capitals</hi> ſtand each for ſome <hi>notable</hi> or <hi>cuſtomary</hi> words, as <hi>S. P. Q. R.</hi> ſtood for <hi>Senatus Populus-que Romanus,</hi> The Senate and People of <hi>Rome.</hi> After them, <hi>we</hi> are accuſtomed to uſe them <hi>ſeveral</hi> ways: As for <hi>marks</hi> upon <hi>Books, Plate,</hi> and <hi>Moveables;</hi> and for <hi>denotations</hi> of ſome <hi>eminent</hi> and <hi>memorable Names</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles,</hi> as J. R. <hi>Jacobus</hi> Rex, King <hi>James; M. R. Maria Regina,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> A. C. <hi>Archi-Epiſcopus Cantuarienſis,</hi> The Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> S. A. C. <hi>Summus Angliae Cancellarius,</hi> The Lord High Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. S. S. T. D. <hi>Sacro Sanctae Theologiae Doctor;</hi> or D. D. Doctor of Divinity; B. D. Batchelor of Divinity; L. L. D. Doctor of Laws; R. S. S. Fellow of the Royal Society; M. A. Maſter of Arts; V. <hi>vide,</hi> ſee; N. B. <hi>Nota benè,</hi> note well; P. P. Penny Poſt; ℞ <hi>Recipe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner, the <hi>Romans</hi> uſed <hi>Capitals</hi> for their <hi>numeral</hi> Letters and Figures, which are ſtill in <hi>uſe</hi> amongſt moſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Nations on <hi>Houſes, Monuments</hi> and <hi>Books,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Characters, powers</hi> and <hi>ſignifications</hi> are as follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>One</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>II</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Two</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>III</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Three</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IV</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>Four</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>V</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>Five</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VI</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>Six</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VII</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>Seven</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VIII</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>Eight</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IX</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>Nine</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>X</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>Ten</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XI</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>Eleven</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XII</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>Twelve</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XIII</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>Thirteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XIV</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>Fourteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XV</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Fifteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XVI</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>Sixteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XVII</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>Seventeen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XVIII</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>Eighteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179339:7"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XIX</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>Nineteen</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XX</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>Twenty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XXX</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>Thirty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XL</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>Forty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>L</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>Fifty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>LX</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>Sixty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>LXX</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>Seventy</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>LXXX</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>Eighty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XC</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>Ninety</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>C</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CX</cell>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and ten</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CXX</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and twenty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CXXX</cell>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and thirty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CXL</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and forty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CL</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and fifty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CLX</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and ſixty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CLXX</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and ſeventy</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CLXXX</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and eighty</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CXC</cell>
                        <cell>190</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred and ninety</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>CC</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>Two hundred</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>D or D</cell>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                        <cell>Five hundred</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>M or M</cell>
                        <cell>1000</cell>
                        <cell>One thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ↁ</cell>
                        <cell>5000</cell>
                        <cell>Five thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ↂ</cell>
                        <cell>10000</cell>
                        <cell>Ten thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ↇ</cell>
                        <cell>50000</cell>
                        <cell>Fifty thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ↈ</cell>
                        <cell>100000</cell>
                        <cell>One hundred thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:rn500000"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>roman 500000</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>500000</cell>
                        <cell>Five hundred thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:rn1000000"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>roman 1000000</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1000000</cell>
                        <cell>Ten hundred thouſand</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>MDCLXXXVI</cell>
                        <cell>1686</cell>
                        <cell>One thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred eighty ſix.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>As thus <hi>Letters</hi> expreſs <hi>Figures,</hi> ſo ſometimes we find <hi>Figures</hi> expreſſing <hi>Letters,</hi> as 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> for <hi>Quarto,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> for <hi>Octavo,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> for <hi>Duodecimo,</hi> 9 for <hi>us,</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">ber</hi> for <hi>September,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">ber</hi> for <hi>October,</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">ber</hi> for <hi>November,</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">ber</hi> for <hi>December,</hi> X<hi rend="sup">ian</hi> for <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abbreviations</hi> are uſed in <hi>writing</hi> for the more <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency</hi> of writing <hi>ſhort,</hi> and <hi>diſpatching</hi> buſineſs; and they are as follow.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> for <hi>Majeſtie</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sa. <hi>Sacred</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Exc<hi rend="sup">ll.</hi> 
                     <hi>Excellency</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gr. <hi>Grace</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hig<hi rend="sup">ſs</hi> 
                     <hi>Highneſs</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lo<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
                     <hi>Lordſhip</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>La<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
                     <hi>Ladiſhip</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
                     <hi>Biſhop</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wo<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
                     <hi>Worſhip</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wo<hi rend="sup">ll</hi> 
                     <hi>Worſhipful</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Sir</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Maſter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Eſq; <hi>Eſquire</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Yeo. <hi>Yeoman</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sch. <hi>Scholar</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Qu. <hi>Queſtion</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Anſ. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gen<hi rend="sup">ll</hi> 
                     <hi>General</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Governour</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gov<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Government</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
                     <hi>Honourable</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Illuſt. <hi>Illuſtrious</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Knight</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Lord</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Capt. <hi>Captain</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Coll. <hi>Collonel</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Com<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Commiſſioner</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Adm<hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
                     <hi>Admiral</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Adm<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Merch<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for <hi>Merchant</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ex<hi rend="sup">ers</hi> 
                     <hi>Executors</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>C<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Creditor</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Debitor</hi> or <hi>Doctor</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Obj. <hi>Objection</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sol. <hi>Solution</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>D<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Delivered</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Re<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Received</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>Miſtris</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Liev<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Lievtenant</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>Letters</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>obt. <hi>obtain</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Aug. Auguſt</item>
                  <item>Chap. <hi>Chapter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ver. <hi>Verſe</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>P. <hi>Page</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lin. <hi>Line</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fol. Folio</item>
                  <item>Md. Memorandum</item>
                  <item>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Saint</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>P<hi rend="sup">nts</hi> 
                     <hi>Preſents</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pet<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Petitioner</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>p<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>paid</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Req<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> 
                     <hi>Requeſt</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sev<hi rend="sup">rl</hi> 
                     <hi>Several</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Tre<hi rend="sup">re</hi> 
                     <hi>Treaſure</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Tre<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 
                     <hi>Treaſury</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Yo<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>Yours</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>the</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:179339:8"/>
                  <item>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for <hi>that</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>what</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>y<hi rend="sup">m</hi> 
                     <hi>them</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>&amp; <hi>and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>viz. <hi>videlicet,</hi> to wit</item>
                  <item>ꝑ <hi>per</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>ꝓ <hi>pro</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g> 
                     <hi>pre</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>q<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>containing</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>q<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>quarters</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                     <hi>which</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>with</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>&amp;c. <hi>and ſo forth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:9"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179339:9"/>
            <head>Engliſh Orthography. PART II.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of <hi>Spelling</hi> and <hi>Dividing</hi> of <hi>Syllables.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFTER this <hi>brief</hi> Conſideration of the <hi>ſeveral</hi> Letters in the <hi>Alphabet,</hi> according to their <hi>ſingle</hi> capacities, I ſhall now <hi>proceed</hi> to ſpeak of them (as it were) <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd</hi> in <hi>ſociety,</hi> with reference to <hi>others,</hi> being <hi>reduc'd</hi> within the <hi>compaſs</hi> and <hi>dominion</hi> of words.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who have <hi>learnt</hi> the <hi>Grammar,</hi> if they but mind <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy,</hi> accompliſh themſelves in <hi>one</hi> (though not the <hi>leaſt</hi>) part of <hi>learning.</hi> And although we find <hi>many</hi> by a fatal <hi>experience</hi> to <hi>neglect</hi> it, and arrive onely to a <hi>mediocrity</hi> of <hi>perfection,</hi> and too frequently not <hi>that</hi> neither, to the <hi>reproach</hi> of <hi>pretenders</hi> to <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Orthography</hi> being an <hi>eſſential</hi> part thereof: Yet my <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> practical <hi>Rules</hi> are for the moſt part <hi>deſign'd</hi> for the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of thoſe who <hi>never</hi> had (or have caſually neglected) the <hi>opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of Learning.</p>
               <p>I give theſe <hi>Rules</hi> from my own <hi>practice</hi> and experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have <hi>taught</hi> ſeveral of <hi>both Sexes,</hi> who were altogether <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> of any <hi>Grammar,</hi> to <hi>ſpell</hi> true <hi>Engliſh</hi> to a very great <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> and indeed <hi>better</hi> than many who have learnt the <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> and <hi>other</hi> things alſo.</p>
               <p>§ The <hi>onely</hi> way for <hi>Ladies,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> who have not had <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar-erudition,</hi> is to obſerve <hi>carefully</hi> theſe following <hi>Directions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. When you have <hi>attain'd</hi> to write <hi>indifferently</hi> well, <hi>pry</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly into every <hi>word</hi> you write, and diligently <hi>enquire</hi> how it is <hi>ſpelt,</hi> and <hi>written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:179339:10"/>2. You muſt get <hi>ſomebody</hi> to reade <hi>ſoftly</hi> and eaſily to you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you can <hi>follow</hi> him at firſt, <hi>ſpelling</hi> as <hi>well</hi> as you can your own way; And when you have <hi>done,</hi> let <hi>ſome</hi> who have <hi>skill,</hi> reade over what you have <hi>written,</hi> and <hi>correct</hi> it: by doing this <hi>frequently,</hi> you will not <hi>fail</hi> to <hi>attain</hi> a conſiderable <hi>perfection</hi> in ſmall time.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When you can <hi>ſpell</hi> pretty well, <hi>uſe</hi> your ſelf to <hi>read</hi> what your <hi>Genius</hi> moſt leads you to; and when you <hi>read,</hi> it is very <hi>convenient</hi> to keep an <hi>Alphabet</hi> of all the <hi>hard words</hi> you find, of whoſe <hi>ſignification</hi> you are <hi>ignorant:</hi> and for your <hi>farther</hi> inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ask ſome <hi>underſtanding</hi> perſon, or at your own <hi>leaſure</hi> apply your ſelf to a <hi>Dictionary,</hi> where you may get the <hi>true meaning</hi> and <hi>ſignification</hi> of any <hi>word</hi> you ſhall find.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>method</hi> you will not only <hi>learn</hi> to <hi>ſpell</hi> well, and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> the <hi>meaning</hi> of all words you meet with, but alſo to <hi>read well;</hi> that is, to have a <hi>true notion</hi> in your <hi>mind</hi> of what you <hi>read:</hi> for, it is hardly <hi>poſſible</hi> for any man to <hi>read</hi> well that which he does <hi>not underſtand.</hi> He may <hi>perform</hi> ſuch a thing ſometimes, I confeſs, by <hi>chance,</hi> and <hi>accidentally;</hi> but it is granted on all hands, that there is a <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>ſound</hi> and of <hi>poſture,</hi> as well as of <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>Syllables,</hi> and, that</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>He who does <hi>read,</hi> and <hi>knows</hi> not the <hi>full</hi> ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Hath but the <hi>pratling Parrot</hi>'s Eloquence.</l>
                  <l>But he that <hi>reads,</hi> and <hi>underſtands</hi> aright,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Humours</hi> the <hi>Senſe,</hi> and <hi>charms</hi> you with <hi>delight.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Let <hi>ſome</hi> people <hi>read,</hi> and you can make <hi>nothing</hi> at all of the <hi>matter:</hi> Some again of a <hi>truly ingenious</hi> frame, and <hi>nice conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (for <hi>ſo</hi> I muſt <hi>eſteem</hi> him that <hi>reads</hi> well) do give ſuch <hi>life</hi> and <hi>motion</hi> to the <hi>things,</hi> that they in a manner <hi>inchant</hi> the <hi>hearers,</hi> and make them <hi>imbibe,</hi> and throughly <hi>underſtand</hi> the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>meaning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What makes <hi>Plays</hi> more <hi>taking</hi> from the <hi>Actor's</hi> mouth, than when the <hi>ſame words</hi> are read in <hi>downright</hi> print, proceeds from this <hi>Source,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Poet</hi> hath <hi>inſtructed</hi> the <hi>Player</hi> with the moſt <hi>intimate</hi> intrigue of his <hi>own mind,</hi> and (as I may ſay) with the very <hi>heart</hi> of his <hi>intention.</hi> Whereas the <hi>print</hi> is only the <hi>dead Letter, dull</hi> and <hi>inſenſible,</hi> having nothing but the <hi>ſtock</hi> of the Poet's <hi>wit</hi> to <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> on, and <hi>engage</hi> the <hi>Reader,</hi> who, if he hath <hi>ſeen</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> Play acted, is oftentimes <hi>compell'd</hi> to be <hi>beholden</hi> to his <hi>Memory</hi> for his <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179339:10"/>
               <p>In <hi>writing</hi> you muſt not <hi>divide</hi> a <hi>Syllable, that is,</hi> you are not to <hi>write</hi> one <hi>half,</hi> or one <hi>Letter</hi> of a <hi>Syllable</hi> in <hi>one</hi> Line, and the <hi>reſt</hi> in the <hi>next:</hi> but if your <hi>Line</hi> will not <hi>contain</hi> all your <hi>word,</hi> you muſt either <hi>divide</hi> it <hi>rightly,</hi> or <hi>write</hi> all your <hi>word</hi> in the <hi>next</hi> Line, which is the <hi>beſt way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a <hi>Conſonant</hi> is <hi>doubled,</hi> or when two <hi>Conſonants</hi> come <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> they are <hi>divided</hi> thus: the <hi>one</hi> to the <hi>firſt</hi> Syllable; the <hi>other</hi> to the <hi>laſt:</hi> as <hi>Ad-der, dif-fer, ſel-dom, Trum-pet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a <hi>Conſonant</hi> come <hi>between</hi> two Vowels, you muſt <hi>join</hi> the <hi>Conſonant</hi> to the <hi>Vowel</hi> following it: as <hi>be-came, re-port</hi> [x] one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted, which is evermore <hi>annexed</hi> to the <hi>Vowel</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: as <hi>Ox-en, ex-er-ciſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a word conſiſt of two <hi>words,</hi> and the <hi>firſt</hi> part of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> had the <hi>ſilent</hi> [e] in the <hi>ſimple</hi> word, it retaineth it in the <hi>compound,</hi> and is <hi>joined</hi> to the <hi>Conſonant</hi> before it: as <hi>where-of, where-in, where-by, ſafe-guard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If two or three Conſonants which can <hi>begin</hi> words, come <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt</hi> two Vowels, they muſt not be <hi>parted,</hi> but muſt even <hi>ſtrike</hi> in with the <hi>Vowel</hi> following: as <hi>con-ſtrain, con-ſtruct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are the</hi> Conſonants <hi>which</hi> begin <hi>words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>bl, br, cl, ch, cr, dr, dw, fl, fr, gl, gn, gr, kl, kn, kr, ph, pl, pr, ſc, ſh, sk, ſl, ſm, ſn, ſp, ſq, ſt, ſw, th, tr, tw, wh, wr.</p>
               <p>Sometimes there are three Conſonants together at the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement</hi> of <hi>words,</hi> and theſe are <hi>chr, phr, ſcr, ſhr, ſpr, ſtr; thr.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus in the <hi>world</hi> of <hi>Letters</hi> there is <hi>found</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>beauteous</hi> harmony of <hi>place</hi> and <hi>ſound,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As in the <hi>greater</hi> World and <hi>myſtick Book</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>lovely</hi> Nature nothing is <hi>miſtook:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So when each <hi>Letter</hi> hath its <hi>proper place,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>words</hi> run <hi>ſweet,</hi> and give the <hi>Writing grace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179339:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Monoſyllables.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SPelling</hi> well is the <hi>dividing</hi> words into <hi>Syllables,</hi> and <hi>allotting</hi> to each <hi>Syllable</hi> its due and <hi>proper</hi> Letters, as <hi>vi-o-lence, vi-li-fy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt <hi>words</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue are <hi>ſpelt</hi> according to the <hi>ſound:</hi> but it is <hi>beſt</hi> to adhere to the <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>true ſpelling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For your better <hi>conveniency</hi> and more <hi>happy</hi> procedure in <hi>this</hi> kind, I have carefully <hi>collected</hi> and <hi>methodically</hi> digeſted the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> part of thoſe <hi>words</hi> which have any <hi>difficulty</hi> in them of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and ſome of <hi>more</hi> Syllables, whereby you may ſee how they are <hi>ſpelt,</hi> and from <hi>whence</hi> you may draw ſuch <hi>general deductions</hi> and <hi>obſervations,</hi> as may <hi>extend</hi> to the right <hi>underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>ſpelling</hi> any word you <hi>meet</hi> withal.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>A <hi>Table</hi> of <hi>words</hi> of <hi>one</hi> Syllable.</head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>A</head>
                        <item>Acre</item>
                        <item>act</item>
                        <item>ancle</item>
                        <item>angle</item>
                        <item>awl.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>B</head>
                        <item>Bath</item>
                        <item>badge</item>
                        <item>breadth</item>
                        <item>brought</item>
                        <item>bought</item>
                        <item>bough</item>
                        <item>branch.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>C</head>
                        <item>Chriſt</item>
                        <item>church</item>
                        <item>cleanſe</item>
                        <item>caught</item>
                        <item>check</item>
                        <item>cloath</item>
                        <item>cough.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>D</head>
                        <item>Dawn</item>
                        <item>dearth</item>
                        <item>drudge</item>
                        <item>draught</item>
                        <item>dough</item>
                        <item>drought</item>
                        <item>dumb</item>
                        <item>dwarf.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>E</head>
                        <item>Earn</item>
                        <item>enough</item>
                        <item>eight</item>
                        <item>ews</item>
                        <item>eyes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>F</head>
                        <item>Fault</item>
                        <item>filth</item>
                        <item>flight</item>
                        <item>fraught</item>
                        <item>friend</item>
                        <item>fringe</item>
                        <item>fright.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>G</head>
                        <item>God</item>
                        <item>glad</item>
                        <item>ghoſt</item>
                        <item>grief</item>
                        <item>growth</item>
                        <item>grudge</item>
                        <item>gueſt</item>
                        <item>guide.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>H</head>
                        <item>Health</item>
                        <item>hatch</item>
                        <item>hearth</item>
                        <item>height</item>
                        <item>hymns.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>J</head>
                        <item>Judge</item>
                        <item>joint</item>
                        <item>juice.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>K</head>
                        <item>Knight</item>
                        <item>knives</item>
                        <item>knots.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>L</head>
                        <item>League</item>
                        <item>laugh</item>
                        <item>length</item>
                        <item>light.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>M</head>
                        <item>Month</item>
                        <item>might</item>
                        <item>mouth</item>
                        <item>mulct</item>
                        <item>myrrh.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>N</head>
                        <item>Naught</item>
                        <item>neigh</item>
                        <item>nigh</item>
                        <item>night</item>
                        <item>nought.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>O</head>
                        <item>Ought</item>
                        <item>oar</item>
                        <item>oaths</item>
                        <item>oaks.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>P</head>
                        <item>Plight</item>
                        <item>plunge</item>
                        <item>plague</item>
                        <item>pierce</item>
                        <item>pſalms.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:179339:11"/>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Q</head>
                        <item>Quake</item>
                        <item>quench</item>
                        <item>quacks</item>
                        <item>quick.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>R</head>
                        <item>Reign</item>
                        <item>reins</item>
                        <item>right</item>
                        <item>rough.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>S</head>
                        <item>Schiſm</item>
                        <item>ſcourge</item>
                        <item>ſcour</item>
                        <item>ſearch</item>
                        <item>ſchool</item>
                        <item>ſhrine</item>
                        <item>ſhoo</item>
                        <item>ſhould</item>
                        <item>ſlight</item>
                        <item>ſleight</item>
                        <item>ſigh</item>
                        <item>ſign</item>
                        <item>ſtrength.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>T</head>
                        <item>Taught</item>
                        <item>through</item>
                        <item>tongue</item>
                        <item>twelve</item>
                        <item>twelfth</item>
                        <item>though</item>
                        <item>thought</item>
                        <item>troughs</item>
                        <item>twins.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>V</head>
                        <item>View</item>
                        <item>vaunt</item>
                        <item>vow</item>
                        <item>vail</item>
                        <item>voice.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>U</head>
                        <item>Urge</item>
                        <item>Uſe</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>W</head>
                        <item>Wealth</item>
                        <item>weight</item>
                        <item>weave</item>
                        <item>world</item>
                        <item>wrought</item>
                        <item>write</item>
                        <item>wound</item>
                        <item>wrath</item>
                        <item>wreath</item>
                        <item>wrung</item>
                        <item>wooll</item>
                        <item>woo</item>
                        <item>woe</item>
                        <item>whore.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Y</head>
                        <item>Young</item>
                        <item>youth</item>
                        <item>yaucht</item>
                        <item>year</item>
                        <item>yawn.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Z</head>
                        <item>Zeal</item>
                        <item>Zone.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe are the <hi>words,</hi> to which though <hi>nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath ſting'ly <hi>lent</hi> but a <hi>ſmall ſtature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So as for <hi>Pigmies</hi> they may <hi>paſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet they <hi>great</hi> vertues in <hi>ſmall</hi> ſpace</l>
                  <l>Do <hi>comprehend,</hi> and <hi>ſeem</hi> to be</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Artful</hi> Dames Brachygraphie:</l>
                  <l>For GOD himſelf and <hi>King, World, Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are but the <hi>inch</hi> of <hi>words,</hi> not <hi>ſpan.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than GOD or <hi>World,</hi> what <hi>greater</hi> things,</l>
                  <l>Or, GOD'S Lieutenants, <hi>Sacred Kings?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ev'n <hi>Mar.</hi> who <hi>all words</hi> did <hi>invent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is with <hi>one Syllable content.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> An <hi>Alphabet</hi> of words of <hi>two Syllables.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Ab-ject</item>
                  <item>af-flict</item>
                  <item>an-guiſh</item>
                  <item>aſ-ſwage</item>
                  <item>ab-jure</item>
                  <item>ac-quaint</item>
                  <item>ac-count</item>
                  <item>af-fright</item>
                  <item>aſ-ſault</item>
                  <item>aug-ment</item>
                  <item>ac-cept.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Bap-tiſm</item>
                  <item>birth-right</item>
                  <item>bleſſ-ing</item>
                  <item>blaſ-pheme</item>
                  <item>be-lieve</item>
                  <item>back-bite</item>
                  <item>ban-quet</item>
                  <item>blame-leſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:179339:12"/>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Coun-cil</item>
                  <item>coun-ſel</item>
                  <item>charg-ing</item>
                  <item>crea-ture</item>
                  <item>chal-lenge</item>
                  <item>cym-bals</item>
                  <item>chan-ging</item>
                  <item>caſe-ment</item>
                  <item>cau-ſey</item>
                  <item>con-duct</item>
                  <item>com-pact</item>
                  <item>con-duit.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Da-mage</item>
                  <item>de-ſcribe</item>
                  <item>diſ-charge</item>
                  <item>diſ-ſolve</item>
                  <item>diſ-patch</item>
                  <item>diſ-tinct</item>
                  <item>di-vorce</item>
                  <item>doc-trine</item>
                  <item>dam-ned</item>
                  <item>diſ-ciples</item>
                  <item>diſ-charge</item>
                  <item>daugh-ter.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>E-nough</item>
                  <item>eye-brow</item>
                  <item>ex-cept</item>
                  <item>ex-change</item>
                  <item>earth-quake</item>
                  <item>e-ſchew</item>
                  <item>ex-tinct</item>
                  <item>e-vil.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>Friend-ſhip</item>
                  <item>feign-eth</item>
                  <item>fruſ-trate</item>
                  <item>fa-mine</item>
                  <item>fe-male</item>
                  <item>fierce-neſs</item>
                  <item>flou-riſh</item>
                  <item>four-teenth</item>
                  <item>fro-zen.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Gal-lant</item>
                  <item>grum-ble</item>
                  <item>grudg-ing</item>
                  <item>griev-eth</item>
                  <item>guard-eth</item>
                  <item>gal-lows</item>
                  <item>glut-ton</item>
                  <item>goſ-pel.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Hai-nous</item>
                  <item>high-neſs</item>
                  <item>hence-forth</item>
                  <item>huſ-band</item>
                  <item>hyſ-ſop</item>
                  <item>he-rauld</item>
                  <item>he-brew</item>
                  <item>hire-ling</item>
                  <item>ho-nour.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>J</head>
                  <item>Je-ſus</item>
                  <item>juſ-tice</item>
                  <item>judg-ing</item>
                  <item>jay-lor</item>
                  <item>jour-ney</item>
                  <item>jea-lous</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>I-mage</item>
                  <item>in-creaſe</item>
                  <item>itch-ing.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>K</head>
                  <item>King-dom</item>
                  <item>kinſ-man</item>
                  <item>know-ledge</item>
                  <item>knight-hood</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>Lan-guiſh</item>
                  <item>laugh-ter</item>
                  <item>lec-ture</item>
                  <item>light-ning</item>
                  <item>lov-ing</item>
                  <item>lan-t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rns</item>
                  <item>lat-ter</item>
                  <item>laugh-ing</item>
                  <item>lea-thern</item>
                  <item>leo-pard</item>
                  <item>lodg-ings.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Man-kind</item>
                  <item>maid-en</item>
                  <item>mar-tyr</item>
                  <item>miſ-chief</item>
                  <item>mort-gage</item>
                  <item>mer-chant</item>
                  <item>mur-ther</item>
                  <item>migh-ty</item>
                  <item>moiſt-ure</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>Neigh-bour</item>
                  <item>naugh-ty</item>
                  <item>nei-ther</item>
                  <item>neg-lect</item>
                  <item>nor-thern</item>
                  <item>nour-iſh.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>Off-ſpring</item>
                  <item>ob-ject</item>
                  <item>ob-ſcure</item>
                  <item>op-preſs</item>
                  <item>or-chard</item>
                  <item>ob-tain</item>
                  <item>o-racle.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Pru-dence</item>
                  <item>par-lour</item>
                  <item>pave-ment</item>
                  <item>par-tridge</item>
                  <item>pen-knife</item>
                  <item>peo-ple</item>
                  <item>pe-riſh</item>
                  <item>pil-grim</item>
                  <item>pic-ture</item>
                  <item>prieſt-hood</item>
                  <item>preach-er</item>
                  <item>purg-ing.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Q</head>
                  <item>Quak-er</item>
                  <item>quar-rel</item>
                  <item>quick-en.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Re-venge</item>
                  <item>re-joice</item>
                  <item>re-proach</item>
                  <item>re-ſcue</item>
                  <item>re-ceive</item>
                  <item>reck-on</item>
                  <item>re-ſtraint</item>
                  <item>ru-mours.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Sab bath</item>
                  <item>ſcourg-ing</item>
                  <item>ſcrip-ture</item>
                  <item>ſack-cloath</item>
                  <item>ſafe-guard</item>
                  <item>ſa-lute</item>
                  <item>ſcan-dal</item>
                  <item>ſcor-ner</item>
                  <item>ſhip-wrack</item>
                  <item>ſlaugh-ter.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>Tranſ-greſs</item>
                  <item>tranſ-late</item>
                  <item>trea-ſure</item>
                  <item>threa-ten</item>
                  <item>to-ken</item>
                  <item>treſ-paſs</item>
                  <item>tri-umph</item>
                  <item>tri-bute</item>
                  <item>twi-light.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Vain-ly</item>
                  <item>val-ley</item>
                  <item>va-pour</item>
                  <item>veſ-ſel</item>
                  <item>vine-yard.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>U</head>
                  <item>U-nite</item>
                  <item>un-juſt</item>
                  <item>uſe-ful.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>Writ-ing</item>
                  <item>wa-ges</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:12"/>
                  <item>wed-lock</item>
                  <item>weigh-ing</item>
                  <item>whi-ther</item>
                  <item>work-man</item>
                  <item>writ-ten.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Y</head>
                  <item>Yeo-man</item>
                  <item>yel-low</item>
                  <item>yiel-ding.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Z</head>
                  <item>Zea-lous.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>Contemplate <hi>Vertue</hi>'s charms: her very <hi>name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>fill</hi> and <hi>ſweeten</hi> all the <hi>breath</hi> of <hi>Fame.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of old, fond <hi>Lovers,</hi> in the <hi>Bark</hi> of <hi>Trees</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Incis'd</hi> their <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> names, there to encreaſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vertue</hi> thy <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> be: and <hi>write</hi> her <hi>name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thy <hi>heart,</hi> as <hi>clear</hi> as is thy flame:</l>
                  <l>And then no doubt<note n="†" place="margin">Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</note> 
                     <hi>two ſyllables</hi> will ſoon</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bring</hi> unto thee <hi>wealth, honour</hi> and <hi>renown.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Paradigm<hi>'s of Words of</hi> three Syllables.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Ac-com-pliſh</item>
                  <item>ac-know-ledge</item>
                  <item>ac-cep-tance</item>
                  <item>ac-cor-ding</item>
                  <item>ac-quaint-ance</item>
                  <item>ad-vo-cate</item>
                  <item>af-flict-ed</item>
                  <item>af-ter-ward</item>
                  <item>an-ſwer-ed</item>
                  <item>aſ-ſur-ance.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Back-bit-ers</item>
                  <item>bap-tiz-ing</item>
                  <item>bar-bar-ous</item>
                  <item>be-guil-ed</item>
                  <item>be-liev-ers</item>
                  <item>blaſ-phem-er</item>
                  <item>bleſſ-ed-neſs</item>
                  <item>bar-ren-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Cham-pi-on</item>
                  <item>chan-cel-lor</item>
                  <item>ce-le-brate</item>
                  <item>chaſ-tiſ-eth</item>
                  <item>cheer-ful-neſs</item>
                  <item>chro-ni-cles</item>
                  <item>chriſ-ti-ans</item>
                  <item>cir-cum-ſpect</item>
                  <item>com-mon-wealth</item>
                  <item>che-ru-bims</item>
                  <item>car-bun-cles</item>
                  <item>care-ful-neſs</item>
                  <item>con-quer-ours.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Di-vorce-ment</item>
                  <item>de-creaſ-ed</item>
                  <item>de-ci-ded</item>
                  <item>de-fam-ing</item>
                  <item>de-ſcrib-ed</item>
                  <item>de-ſir-ous</item>
                  <item>diſ-tri-bute</item>
                  <item>drow-ſi-neſs</item>
                  <item>de-trac-tor.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>En-large-ment</item>
                  <item>en-dea-vours</item>
                  <item>eſ-pouſ-als</item>
                  <item>en-croach-ing</item>
                  <item>en-cour-age</item>
                  <item>en-graft-ed</item>
                  <item>eſ-ti-mate</item>
                  <item>e-qual-ly</item>
                  <item>ec-ſta-cy.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:13"/>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>Faint-heart-ed</item>
                  <item>for-ward-neſs</item>
                  <item>frank-in-cenſe</item>
                  <item>fil-thi-neſs</item>
                  <item>fa-vour-able</item>
                  <item>fur-ni-ture</item>
                  <item>for-bid-den.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Gain-ſay-er</item>
                  <item>gar-ri-ſon</item>
                  <item>gor-ge-ous</item>
                  <item>go-ver-nors</item>
                  <item>griev-ouſ-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Hand-ker-chief</item>
                  <item>haugh-ti-neſs</item>
                  <item>he-re-ſies</item>
                  <item>huſ-band-ry</item>
                  <item>hy-po-crite.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>J</head>
                  <item>Jea-lou-ſy</item>
                  <item>Jeo-par-dy.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>Im-pla-cable</item>
                  <item>Im-put-eth</item>
                  <item>In-fam-ous.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>K</head>
                  <item>Kenſ-ing-town</item>
                  <item>kinſ-wo-man</item>
                  <item>kind-heart-ed.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>Liev-ten-ant</item>
                  <item>li-ber-tines</item>
                  <item>lan-guiſh-ed</item>
                  <item>lov-li-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Mi-ni-ſter</item>
                  <item>meſ-ſi-as</item>
                  <item>ma-jeſ-ty</item>
                  <item>me-di-cine</item>
                  <item>me-di-tate</item>
                  <item>ma-giſ-trate</item>
                  <item>main-ten-ance</item>
                  <item>miſ-chiev-ous.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>Nigh-tin-gale</item>
                  <item>nou-riſh-ing</item>
                  <item>ne-glect-ing</item>
                  <item>ne-gli-gent.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>Ob-ſerv-ed</item>
                  <item>off-ſcour-ing</item>
                  <item>of-ten-times</item>
                  <item>o-ver-charge</item>
                  <item>op-preſſ-ing</item>
                  <item>out-land-iſh.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Pa-tri-arch</item>
                  <item>pa-ti-ence</item>
                  <item>per-ceiv-eſt</item>
                  <item>per-ſwa-ding</item>
                  <item>pleaſ-ant-neſs</item>
                  <item>per-ju-ry.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Q</head>
                  <item>Queſ-ti-ons</item>
                  <item>quan-ti-ty</item>
                  <item>que-ru-lous</item>
                  <item>qui-et-neſs</item>
                  <item>quar-rel-ſom.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Re-mem-ber</item>
                  <item>re-ceiv-ed</item>
                  <item>re-deem-er</item>
                  <item>re-main-der</item>
                  <item>re-proach-ed</item>
                  <item>re-pro-bate.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Sa-cri-fice</item>
                  <item>Sa-cri-ledge</item>
                  <item>ſchool-maſ-ter</item>
                  <item>ſe-pa-rate</item>
                  <item>ſe-pul-chre</item>
                  <item>ſoul-di-er.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>Thank-ful-neſs</item>
                  <item>ta-ber-nacle</item>
                  <item>ten-der-neſs</item>
                  <item>teſ-ti-fie</item>
                  <item>tri-umph-ing.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Vain-glo-ry</item>
                  <item>va-ni-ties</item>
                  <item>ven-ge-ance</item>
                  <item>vic-tu-als.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:13"/>
                  <head>U</head>
                  <item>Up-right-ly</item>
                  <item>un-will-ing</item>
                  <item>un-wor-thy</item>
                  <item>up-per-moſt</item>
                  <item>ut-ter-ance.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>Wan-ton-neſs</item>
                  <item>wick-ed-neſs</item>
                  <item>wil-der-neſs</item>
                  <item>wit-ting-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>X</head>
                  <item>Xe-no-phon.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Y</head>
                  <item>Yoke-fel-low</item>
                  <item>Yeſ ter-day.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Z</head>
                  <item>Zo-di-ack</item>
                  <item>Zea-louſ-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>Hail great <hi>Tri-ſyllable!</hi> eternal <hi>Three!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Three</hi> in <hi>One,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> in TRINITY!</l>
                  <l>Thou <hi>matchleſs</hi> and <hi>unfathomable</hi> Myſterie!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>With Thee <hi>all</hi> ſhould <hi>begin</hi> and all ſhould <hi>end,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If it end <hi>well:</hi> If't would it ſelf <hi>commend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>fame,</hi> and <hi>general uſe,</hi> it muſt have Thee its <hi>friend.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Wherefore, let all <hi>true writers</hi> here <hi>agree,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with thy <hi>Pen-men</hi> all <hi>true Chriſtians be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And own this <hi>awfull truth,</hi> which is well worthy <hi>Thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Examples <hi>of Words of</hi> four Syllables.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Ac-com-pliſh-ment</item>
                  <item>a-bo-liſh-ed</item>
                  <item>ac-know-ledg-ed</item>
                  <item>af-fec-ti-on</item>
                  <item>ap-pre-hend-ing</item>
                  <item>ac-cord-ing-ly</item>
                  <item>al-to-ge-ther.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Bar-bar-ouſ-neſs</item>
                  <item>blaſ-phem-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>burnt-ſa-cri-fice</item>
                  <item>blood-guil-ti-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Cir-cum-ciſ-ing</item>
                  <item>con-cu-piſ-cence</item>
                  <item>con-ſci-en-ces</item>
                  <item>col-lec-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:14"/>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Di-mi-niſh-ed</item>
                  <item>de-ceit-ful-neſs</item>
                  <item>diſ-ap-point-eth</item>
                  <item>de-ſcrip-ti-on</item>
                  <item>diſ-poſ-ſeſſ-ed.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>E-van-ge-liſt</item>
                  <item>e-ſta-bliſh-ed</item>
                  <item>en-dea-voured.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>For-get-ful-neſs</item>
                  <item>foun-da-ti-on</item>
                  <item>fa-mi-li-ars.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Ge-ner-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>gor-ge-ouſ-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Hy-po-cri-ſy</item>
                  <item>hu-mi-li-ty</item>
                  <item>hu-mour-ſom-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>Ig-no-mi-ny</item>
                  <item>in-du-ſtri-ous</item>
                  <item>i-ma-gin-eth</item>
                  <item>i-ni-qui-ty.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>Lov-ing-kind-neſs</item>
                  <item>Li-ber-al-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Ma-le-fac-tors</item>
                  <item>mar-vel-louſ-ly</item>
                  <item>mag-ni-fi-cence.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>Not-with-ſtand-ing</item>
                  <item>ne-ceſ-ſa-ry</item>
                  <item>ne-cro-man-cy.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>O-ver-throw-ing</item>
                  <item>op-preſ-ſi-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Pre-ſump-ti-on</item>
                  <item>per-ad-ven-ture</item>
                  <item>per-ſe-cut-er.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Q</head>
                  <item>Queſ-ti-on-ing</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Re-bel-li-on</item>
                  <item>re-proach-ful-ly</item>
                  <item>righ-te-ouſ-neſs</item>
                  <item>re-demp-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Sump-tu-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>ſa-cri-fi-cer</item>
                  <item>ſanc-tu-ar-ies.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>Tem-peſ-tu-ous</item>
                  <item>tranſ-greſ-ſi-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Va-li-ant-ly</item>
                  <item>ver-tu-ouſ-ly</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>U</head>
                  <item>Un-mer-ci-ful</item>
                  <item>un-cor-rupt-ed</item>
                  <item>un-be-liev-ers.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>Wel-be-lov-ed</item>
                  <item>won-der-ful-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Four Syllables</hi> if you would <hi>underſtand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mind well <hi>theſe words,</hi> how their <hi>diviſions</hi> ly,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>which</hi> you may the <hi>hardeſt</hi> then <hi>command</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And get <hi>perfection</hi> to your ſelf <hi>thereby.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Words of</hi> five Syllables.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Al-le-go-ri-cal</item>
                  <item>ad-mo-ni-ti-on</item>
                  <item>a-po-the-ca-ry.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Be-ne-dic-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Cir-cum-ſpec-ti-on</item>
                  <item>con-ſum-ma-ti-on</item>
                  <item>con-fe-de-ra-cy</item>
                  <item>con-tri-bu-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Diſ-o-be-di-ence</item>
                  <item>de-li-be-rate-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>Ex-tor-ti-on-er</item>
                  <item>ex-e-cra-ti-on</item>
                  <item>ex-hor-ta-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>Fer-ment-a-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Gu-ber-na-ti-on</item>
                  <item>ge-ne-a-lo-gy.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Har-mo-ni-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>hy-po-cri-ti-cal.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>J</head>
                  <item>Ju-riſ-dic-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>In-cor-rup-ti-ble</item>
                  <item>in-ſur-rec-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>La-bo-ri-ouſ-neſs</item>
                  <item>la-ſci-vi-ouſ-neſs.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Ma-li-ci-ouſ-neſs</item>
                  <item>miſ-con-ſtruc-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>Non-con-for-mi-ty.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>Oc-cu-pa-ti-on</item>
                  <item>op-por-tu-ni-ty</item>
                  <item>o-ver-ſha-dow-ed.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Pre-ſump-tu-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>pre-me-di-tat-ed.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Re-ſur-rec-ti-on</item>
                  <item>re-ſti-tu-ti-on</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Su-per-ſcrip-ti-on</item>
                  <item>ſuf-fi-ci-en-cy</item>
                  <item>ſu-per-ſti-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>Tranſ-mi-gra-ti-on</item>
                  <item>tri-bu-la-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Vic-to-ri-ouſ-ly</item>
                  <item>vi-ſi-ta-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>U</head>
                  <item>Un-righ-te-ouſ-neſs</item>
                  <item>un-ac-cu-ſtom-ed.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>Whi-ther-ſo-e-ver.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plenty</hi> o'erwhelms, but no <hi>delight</hi> affords</l>
                  <l>In <hi>muſty</hi> Catalogues of <hi>Giant-words:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore with their <hi>tall Worſhips</hi> I ſhall be</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Short,</hi> in regard they have been <hi>long</hi> with <hi>me:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> lies in <hi>Epitome.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> A <hi>Collection</hi> of Words of <hi>ſix</hi> and <hi>ſeven Syllables.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Ad-mi-ni-ſtra-ti-on</item>
                  <item>af-fec-ti-o-nate-ly.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Be-a-ti-fi-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Con-fec-ti-on-ar-ies</item>
                  <item>Cir-cum-lo-cu-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Diſ-ſi-mu-la-ti-on</item>
                  <item>De-nun-ci-a-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>Ex-a-mi-na-ti-on</item>
                  <item>ex-com-mu-ni-ca-ti-on</item>
                  <item>E-le-e-mo-ſi-na-ry.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>Fruc-ti-fi-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Glo-ri-fi-ca-ti-on</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Hu-mi-li-a-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>Im-mu-ta-bi-li-ty</item>
                  <item>In-ter-pre-ta-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Mul-ti-pli-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Pu-ri-fi-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Re-ge-ne-ra-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Sanc-ti-fi-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Vi-li-fi-ca-ti-on.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:15"/>
                  <l>The longeſt <hi>words,</hi> and the moſt tedious <hi>Arts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are <hi>overcome</hi> by <hi>willing</hi> hands and hearts.</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Art</hi> ſo <hi>hard,</hi> what <hi>Science</hi> ſo <hi>obſcure;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That can the <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Induſtry</hi> endure?</l>
                  <l>The <hi>honour</hi>'s high of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>great command,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>greater</hi> far it is to <hi>underſtand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Theſe words are ſufficient for any Learner, abundance of words diſcourage more than they inſtruct; for if a Youth can once ſpell theſe, he may ſpell any: thoſe of riper underſtanding and years need only read theſe words over; but it is very convenient for Youth to be carefully inſtructed to know them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Sentences.</head>
               <p>ALL <hi>learned</hi> men in the <hi>ſeveral</hi> ages of <hi>humane race</hi> have highly <hi>approved</hi> of <hi>ſhort Sentences,</hi> or expreſſing a <hi>Thought</hi> in <hi>few</hi> words.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which are of a long <hi>Ciceronian</hi> ſtrain do not <hi>yet</hi> either want their <hi>excellencies</hi> or <hi>Admirers:</hi> but which of the <hi>two</hi> beſt <hi>deſerves</hi> the <hi>Lawrel,</hi> doth not belong to my <hi>purpoſe</hi> to <hi>diſpute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, this is undoubtedly true of them <hi>both,</hi> that whether you are to <hi>write</hi> either the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other,</hi> it is your <hi>beſt way</hi> to begin the <hi>Line</hi> at every <hi>full ſtop,</hi> or <hi>end</hi> of a <hi>ſentence.</hi> This <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> indeed, if it were in <hi>all</hi> caſes <hi>obſerved,</hi> would take up <hi>too</hi> much <hi>room,</hi> and <hi>ſwell</hi> Books to a <hi>great Volume:</hi> and therefore a <hi>great Letter</hi> hath been <hi>appointed</hi> to <hi>begin</hi> each <hi>Sentence.</hi> But in <hi>writing</hi> any <hi>buſineſs,</hi> where we have room <hi>enough,</hi> I may <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend</hi> it not only as <hi>neceſſary,</hi> but <hi>beautiful</hi> for the Readers <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men have that admirable <hi>dexterity</hi> of <hi>epitomizing</hi> things, and <hi>couching</hi> ſuch a <hi>world</hi> of <hi>excellent ſenſe</hi> in a few <hi>happy expreſſions,</hi> that the <hi>Readers</hi> not only <hi>admire</hi> them, but are <hi>rapt</hi> into an <hi>ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy</hi> in the <hi>contemplation. Examp. Gr.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a madneſs in Youth, either not to endeavour good Advice, or not to believe till their peril comes upon them, and makes them ſee it to their ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Errours by miſtakes ſhould not be too rigorouſly cenſured; but wilful Errours ſhould not be ſpared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pray often, becauſe thou ſineſt always: Repent quickly, leſt thou die ſuddenly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He is a happy man, that hath all things he deſires: but he who does not deſire, the things he hath not, is happier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miſtruſt no man without ſome cauſe; neither be credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous without proof,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hear no ill of a Friend, nor ſpeak any of an Enemy; Believe not all you hear, nor ſpeak all you believe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Sentence</hi> is the <hi>miniature</hi> of <hi>Thought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of what's truly <hi>great,</hi> a <hi>little draught.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Life, briskneſs,</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi> there, <hi>combine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With an <hi>immenſity</hi> of <hi>rayes</hi> to <hi>ſhine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Ophyr</hi> Gold or <hi>Oriental</hi> Spice</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>like</hi> to the <hi>perfume</hi> of <hi>Sage advice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or is ſo <hi>glittering:</hi> no not <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More in his <hi>glory,</hi> than his <hi>Proverbs</hi> ſhone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:179339:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of <hi>Points</hi> or <hi>Stops</hi> uſed in <hi>Sentences.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>writing</hi> and <hi>reading</hi> of all <hi>Sentences</hi> and <hi>Writings,</hi> the <hi>Points</hi> and <hi>Stops</hi> are to be <hi>judiciouſly</hi> obſerved; otherwiſe we certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> the <hi>Senſe</hi> by <hi>ſailing</hi> without theſe <hi>Guides.</hi> Upon <hi>which</hi> account I have <hi>here</hi> ſet down not only the <hi>Stops</hi> and <hi>Pauſes,</hi> but alſo all <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> uſed for the <hi>better underſtanding</hi> of what we <hi>write</hi> or <hi>read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>Points <hi>or</hi> Stops.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. Comma</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">Characteriz'd <hi>thus</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. Semi-colon</cell>
                        <cell>;</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. Colon</cell>
                        <cell>:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. Period</cell>
                        <cell>.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. Interrogation</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. Admiration</cell>
                        <cell>!</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <head>Notes <hi>of</hi> Direction.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1. Aſteriſm</cell>
                        <cell rows="13">Figured in this manner</cell>
                        <cell>*</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. Hyphen</cell>
                        <cell>-</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. Caret</cell>
                        <cell>⁁</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4. Obelisk or dagger</cell>
                        <cell>†</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5. Separation</cell>
                        <cell>=</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6. Apoſtrophe</cell>
                        <cell>'</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7. Quotation</cell>
                        <cell>“</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. Index</cell>
                        <cell>☞</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9. Parentheſis</cell>
                        <cell>()</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10. Crotchet</cell>
                        <cell>[]</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11. Section</cell>
                        <cell>§</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12. Parallels</cell>
                        <cell>‖</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13. Paragraph</cell>
                        <cell>¶</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. A <hi>Comma</hi> (,) is the <hi>leaſt,</hi> but moſt <hi>frequently</hi> uſed of all, taking very <hi>little breath,</hi> as being almoſt <hi>every-where employed:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe filthy Dreamers defile the Fleſh, deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> Jude <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:179339:17"/>2. A <hi>Semi-colon</hi> (;) hath ſomewhat a greater <hi>ſtreſs</hi> than a <hi>Comma</hi> laid upon it, both as to the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and to the <hi>pauſe:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their throat is an open Sepulchre; with their tongues they uſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; the poiſon of Aſps is under their lips,</hi> Pſalm.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A <hi>Colon</hi> is uſed when there is <hi>full ſenſe</hi> expreſt, but yet the <hi>Sentence</hi> is not <hi>quite ſpent:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's ſake: whether it be to the</hi> KING, <hi>as Supream,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A <hi>Period,</hi> or <hi>Punctum</hi> (.) <hi>concludes</hi> the whole <hi>Sentence:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honour all men. Love the Brotherhood. Fear</hi> GOD. <hi>Honour the</hi> KING, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>four</hi> are truly <hi>intire Sentences</hi> of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and are <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly</hi> written with <hi>Periods:</hi> but any man conſidering the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence</hi> they have <hi>one</hi> upon <hi>another,</hi> may write <hi>them</hi> and <hi>ſuch like</hi> with <hi>Colons,</hi> except the laſt, which muſt of <hi>neceſſity</hi> be concluded with a <hi>full point.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. A Note of <hi>Interrogation</hi> (?) is always plac'd after a <hi>Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What advantage then hath the</hi> Jew? <hi>or what profit is there in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion?</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 3.1.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A mark of <hi>Admiration</hi> (!) muſt not be forgotten, when men <hi>lift</hi> up their <hi>hands</hi> or <hi>voices</hi> by way of <hi>wonder</hi> or <hi>exclamation:</hi> As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh Death! where is thy Sting? Oh Grave! where is thy Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory?</hi> 1 Cor. 15.55.</p>
               <div type="explanation">
                  <head>The Explanation of the Notes of <hi>Direction.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. An <hi>Aſteriſm</hi> (*) is uſed commonly in the <hi>Bible,</hi> when any <hi>Sentence</hi> or <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is <hi>alluded</hi> to, or may be <hi>compared</hi> with <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. A <hi>Hyphen</hi> is (-) a Note of <hi>continuation,</hi> or <hi>connexion;</hi> as <hi>Pal-mal, Common-wealth, workman ſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. A <hi>Caret</hi> (<hi rend="sup">)</hi> is made under the <hi>Line,</hi> when a <hi>word</hi> or <hi>more</hi> is <hi>wanting</hi> and <hi>forgotten,</hi> ſhewing where it muſt be <hi>taken</hi> in.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179339:17"/>4. An <hi>Obelisk</hi> or <hi>Dagger</hi> (†) in the <hi>larger</hi> ſort of <hi>Bibles</hi> is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to <hi>refer</hi> from the <hi>matter</hi> to the <hi>margent,</hi> where it gives an <hi>account</hi> of the <hi>different readings</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. A <hi>Separation</hi> (=) is when <hi>one half</hi> of a <hi>word</hi> is written in <hi>one line,</hi> and the <hi>other half,</hi> or a <hi>Syllable,</hi> is <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>next.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. An <hi>Apoſtrophe</hi> (') is ſet <hi>over</hi> the <hi>place</hi> where a <hi>vowel</hi> is <hi>left</hi> out, as in theſe, <hi>'tis</hi> or <hi>it's</hi> for <hi>it is, train'd</hi> for <hi>trained, bus'neſs</hi> for <hi>buſineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. A <hi>Citation</hi> (“) is, when an <hi>Allegation</hi> out of an <hi>Author</hi> is recited at <hi>length</hi> in his <hi>own words.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. An <hi>Index</hi> (☞) <hi>points</hi> to ſome <hi>notable Saying</hi> or <hi>Sentence</hi> that ought not to <hi>eſcape</hi> without ſome <hi>particular remark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. A <hi>Parentheſis</hi> () denotes, that the <hi>words encloſed</hi> muſt be <hi>ſounded</hi> ſomewhat <hi>different</hi> from the <hi>reſt,</hi> as being an <hi>Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Sentence</hi> that would be <hi>perfect</hi> without it.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. A <hi>Crotchet</hi> [] is much of the <hi>ſame nature</hi> with a <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> and is <hi>uſed</hi> when ſome <hi>extraordinary word</hi> happens, and ought to be <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> or another <hi>Sentence,</hi> or ſomething <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to explain the <hi>meaning</hi> after a <hi>Parentheſis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. A <hi>Section</hi> (§) is when an <hi>ample</hi> diſcourſe is <hi>cut</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> into ſeveral <hi>larger portions,</hi> called <hi>Sections.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>Parallels</hi> (‖) do often <hi>occur</hi> in the margents of <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> when a <hi>Sentence</hi> according to the <hi>Original</hi> may be otherwiſe <hi>phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and the <hi>Senſe</hi> not <hi>corrupted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. A <hi>Paragraph</hi> (¶) uſually <hi>precedes</hi> a <hi>Sentence</hi> which bears no <hi>dependence</hi> on what went <hi>before.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pointing</hi> is of ſuch great <hi>concernment,</hi> eſpecially to <hi>Scholars,</hi> and indeed to <hi>all;</hi> that the <hi>neglect</hi> thereof make Writings <hi>hard</hi> to be <hi>underſtood</hi> or <hi>read;</hi> and commonly that <hi>defect</hi> makes the true meaning either <hi>ignorantly</hi> or <hi>knaviſhly</hi> to be <hi>miſtaken:</hi> as</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, conſent thou not: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining thy feet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pointed otherwiſe, the Senſe is perverted thus;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, conſent thou; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining thy feet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:179339:18"/>
                  <p>By <hi>miſplacing</hi> of <hi>Stops,</hi> or altogether <hi>leaving</hi> them <hi>out,</hi> to be at pleaſure <hi>put in</hi> by <hi>perſons</hi> concern'd, much <hi>miſchief</hi> has been <hi>done</hi> in many <hi>Places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>England</hi> that unfortunate Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the Second was barbarouſly <hi>murthered</hi> by his <hi>Keeper</hi> in <hi>Pont-fract Caſtle,</hi> (by the treachery of <hi>Iſabella</hi> and <hi>Mortimer.</hi>) The Keeper [it ſeems] ſent to <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer</hi> to know what he ſhould do with the <hi>King,</hi> who <hi>anſwered</hi> him by his <hi>Letter</hi> thus: <q>
                        <hi>Edwardum</hi> occidere nolite timere bonum eſt.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To kill King <hi>Edward</hi> refuſe to be afraid is good.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Paſſage</hi> in his <hi>Letter</hi> being <hi>without Stops,</hi> The <hi>Keeper</hi> well-knowing <hi>Mortimer</hi> had no <hi>kindneſs</hi> for the <hi>King,</hi> did as <hi>Mortimer</hi> truly <hi>meant,</hi> that is, <hi>kill'd</hi> the <hi>King;</hi> and when he was juſtly <hi>queſtion'd,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd the <hi>Letter,</hi> which <hi>Mortimer</hi> own'd, but <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> alledg'd that his meaning was <hi>otherwiſe: ſuch</hi> baſe <hi>Tricks</hi> perfidious <hi>Villains</hi> have practiſed to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> Truth, and colour their <hi>Knavery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Such Tricks</hi> are commonly <hi>impoſed</hi> on the <hi>World</hi> by ſuch <hi>villainous</hi> and <hi>diabolical</hi> Miſcreants and <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> who give ſuch <hi>dubious Interpretations</hi> on the <hi>holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to the <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> after the Example of their <hi>Father</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf not able to <hi>anſwer</hi> any thing truly out of the <hi>Heathen Oracles,</hi> reply'd to all <hi>queſtions cunningly,</hi> and ſo <hi>dubiouſly,</hi> that which <hi>way</hi> ſoever the thing <hi>fell</hi> out, he was ſure to <hi>ſeem</hi> to be in the <hi>right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Inſtance. Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi> in his deſcription of <hi>Delphos</hi> writes thus, <hi>Page</hi> 593, <hi>&amp;</hi> 594.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179339:18"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Delphos</hi> renowned in <hi>old times</hi> for the <hi>famous</hi> Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> in which with that of <hi>Jupiter Hammon</hi> in <hi>Marmarica</hi> (now reckon'd as a part of <hi>Aegypt</hi>) were the moſt <hi>famous Oracles</hi> of the <hi>ancient Gentiles:</hi> Dark <hi>Ridles</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> couched and contrived with ſo much <hi>cunning,</hi> that the <hi>meaning</hi> of them was moſt <hi>hidden,</hi> when it was thought moſt <hi>eaſie</hi> to be <hi>diſcerned; Inſtance</hi> of <hi>which,</hi> that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Croeſus</hi> in the <hi>War</hi> by him <hi>projected</hi> againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which was thus delivered;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Croeſus Halyn</hi> penetrans magnam ſubvertit opum vim.</p>
                     <l>When <hi>Croeſus</hi> over <hi>Halys</hi> goes,</l>
                     <l>A mighty Nation he o'erthrows.</l>
                     <p>which he <hi>interpreting</hi> according to his <hi>own hopes,</hi> croſſed the <hi>River,</hi> was <hi>vanquiſhed</hi> by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom conquered.</hi> The like we find of <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> King of <hi>Epyrus,</hi> who before he made <hi>war</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> conſulted with the <hi>Oracle,</hi> and <hi>received</hi> this <hi>anſwer;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <l>Aio te Aeacida Romanos vincere poſſe.</l>
                     <p>which <hi>doubtful</hi> Prediction he thus <hi>conſtrued:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <l>Te poſſe vincere Romanos.</l>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That he ſhould overcome the</hi> Romans; but he found it to his <hi>coſt,</hi> that the <hi>meaning</hi> was, <hi>Romanos poſſe vincere te, That the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhould overcome him;</hi> as indeed it happened.</p>
                     <p>By another <hi>kind</hi> of the <hi>ſame fallacy,</hi> which the <hi>Logicians</hi> call <hi>Amphibolia,</hi> did this great <hi>Enemy</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:179339:19"/> 
                        <hi>Mankind</hi> overthrow <hi>another,</hi> who demanding of the <hi>Oracle</hi> what <hi>Succeſs</hi> he ſhould have in an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition</hi> which he was in <hi>hand</hi> with, received his <hi>anſwer</hi> in theſe <hi>words;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <l>Ibis redibis nunquam per Bella peribis</l>
                     <p>which he <hi>thus</hi> pointing</p>
                     <l>Ibis, redibis, unquam per Bella peribis.</l>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Engag'd</hi> himſelf in the <hi>War,</hi> and was therein <hi>ſlain:</hi> whereupon his <hi>Followers</hi> canvaſing the <hi>Oracle,</hi> found the <hi>meaning</hi> to be thus;</p>
                     <l>Ibis, redibis nunquam; per Bella peribis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Several</hi> others, too long to <hi>relate,</hi> are written: ſuch is the <hi>force</hi> of placing <hi>Stops,</hi> that men have <hi>miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued</hi> their <hi>Friends meaning,</hi> either <hi>ignorantly,</hi> or <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,</hi> to <hi>excuſe</hi> themſelves.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Points are the Compaſs, and the guiding Star</l>
                     <l>By which good Readers all directed are.</l>
                     <l>The life of Reading ſweetly flows from thence;</l>
                     <l>Theſe ill-regarded ſhipwrack all the Senſe.</l>
                     <l>The skilful Readers will the Senſe purſue,</l>
                     <l>And charm their Hearers with their reading true,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe they can give Stops and Points their due.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:179339:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of <hi>Superfluous</hi> Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is a <hi>further perfection</hi> in <hi>Spelling,</hi> which I ſhall not much <hi>dwell upon,</hi> as not being ſo <hi>material</hi> to my <hi>deſign:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is worthy of <hi>obſervation</hi> to the <hi>curious</hi> I ſhall <hi>touch</hi> it a little;</p>
               <p>And that is <hi>leaving out</hi> many <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> letters, which may be <hi>omitted</hi> in ſeveral <hi>words,</hi> and the <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ſenſe</hi> not <hi>loſt:</hi> but to <hi>throw</hi> out all <hi>Letters,</hi> that are <hi>not pronounced</hi> (as ſome deſire) would quite <hi>mar</hi> the <hi>ſenſe:</hi> for by the ſame rule we leave out <hi>[ugh]</hi> in <hi>though,</hi> we ought to leave it out in <hi>bought, dough, bough, thought, cough,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It's true we may leave out <hi>[ugh]</hi> in <hi>though,</hi> and the like when the <hi>ſound</hi> will be <hi>good</hi> without it; but when the <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> is <hi>loſt</hi> by ſuch <hi>omiſſions</hi> it is not <hi>tolerable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some of late leave out <hi>[k]</hi> in <hi>Muſick, Arithmetick, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Logick, heroick</hi> and the <hi>like,</hi> which is <hi>allowable,</hi> theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately <hi>derived</hi> from the <hi>Latine,</hi> which have no <hi>k,</hi> tho' the original <hi>Greek</hi> hath.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>ſilent [u]</hi> may very well be left out in <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, favour,</hi> &amp;c. for the <hi>pronunciation</hi> is the <hi>ſame</hi> without it <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, favor, labor,</hi> and the <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ſignification</hi> are both <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But why ſome are for ſuch a <hi>thorow-reformation,</hi> as to omit <hi>[p]</hi> in <hi>tempt, contempt, ſumptuous, ſymptom,</hi> and the like, I know not, ſince the very <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>ſound</hi> reſts on <hi>[p.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither can I be perſwaded to leave <hi>[e]</hi> out at the end of <hi>bridge, pledge, acknowledge,</hi> becauſe the <hi>final [e]</hi> gives <hi>[g]</hi> its <hi>ſharp ſound:</hi> for by the <hi>ſame reaſon</hi> we may <hi>leave</hi> out the <hi>[e]</hi> in <hi>oblige, huge, language, refuge,</hi> &amp;c. which would make <hi>[g]</hi> have its <hi>hard ſound</hi> and quite alter the <hi>ſenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh it were <hi>poſſible</hi> to make a <hi>general Rule</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>leave</hi> out all <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> Letters that are not in the <hi>pronunciation</hi> ſounded; for then <hi>[gh]</hi> might take its <hi>leave</hi> of <hi>many words:</hi> But firſt to ſatisfie the <hi>curious,</hi> we muſt find <hi>ſome way</hi> to <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> the <hi>ſound</hi> of <hi>ſome words</hi> pronounced <hi>alike,</hi> but written <hi>ſeverally;</hi> as in the words following, ſo much imputed by <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to the <hi>imperfection</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Language, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:179339:20"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>John Wright</hi> the Wheel-wright,</l>
                  <l>Can neither write, nor read right,</l>
                  <l>Yet hates a ſuperſtitious Rite.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe words, likewiſe, are written <hi>differently,</hi> but pronounced almoſt <hi>alike, white, weight, wait, witt, wett.</hi> This ſhews the <hi>impoſſibility</hi> of a <hi>general Rule,</hi> ſo much deſired. <hi>Theſe</hi> and the like, make <hi>ſtrangers</hi> a little <hi>uneaſy;</hi> but to pleaſe <hi>ſtrangers</hi> and make our Language <hi>familiar</hi> to their palat, we muſt not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi> our ſelves, as ſome would have <hi>done, come, ſome,</hi> and the like written thus, <hi>don, com, ſom,</hi> becauſe ſtrangers think they are pronounced <hi>do-ne, co-me, ſo-me.</hi> By this means we muſt bring all <hi>other</hi> words, which more <hi>trouble</hi> them, to their <hi>humour.</hi> There are <hi>few ſtrangers</hi> that can pronounce theſe words, <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, hidden, third, thought, truth, ſloath,</hi> &amp;c. ſo there needs no ſuch <hi>care</hi> for ſtrangers, who can never <hi>attain</hi> to any <hi>perfection</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>Book:</hi> the onely way is by an <hi>able Teacher</hi> or by <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> amongſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> people which I <hi>judge</hi> the <hi>beſt way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Words</hi> derived from the <hi>Latine</hi> muſt <hi>retain</hi> their <hi>natural Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to ſhew their <hi>derivation,</hi> as <hi>contemn, condemn, reſign, reign, flegm,</hi> which come from the <hi>Latine</hi> words, <hi>contemno, condemno, reſigno, regno, flegma,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Some words the <hi>Engliſh</hi> pronounce contrary to the <hi>true Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy,</hi> without any <hi>other reaſon</hi> (as I ſaid before) but becauſe they pronounce nothing through the <hi>throat,</hi> and theſe are <hi>laugh, cough, rough,</hi> &amp;c. which by <hi>cuſtome</hi> are thus alter'd, <hi>laff, coff, roff,</hi> which ſtrangers alſo <hi>ſtickle</hi> at. For conveniency we pronounce alſo <hi>ſigh</hi> as with <hi>th,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Words, <hi>Spelt,</hi> or <hi>Sounded Alike,</hi> but of <hi>Different Significations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAny</hi> words in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue are <hi>ſpelt</hi> alike, and have <hi>divers ſignifications:</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> again have <hi>various intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and are pronounced almoſt <hi>alike,</hi> which gives <hi>trouble</hi> to <hi>young Learners.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:20"/>
               <p>To prevent which, and to <hi>encourage</hi> the <hi>Learner,</hi> I have <hi>col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected</hi> the <hi>hardeſt</hi> of theſe <hi>words</hi> in an <hi>Alphabetical order</hi> as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</p>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ABator,</hi> an Intruder</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abater,</hi> one that leſſens</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abettor,</hi> an Aſſiſter</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Account,</hi> Eſteem</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Account,</hi> of Merchants</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Advice,</hi> Counſel</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adviſe,</hi> to give Counſel</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Altar,</hi> for Sacrifice</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alter,</hi> or Change</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Accidents,</hi> Chances</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Accidence,</hi> for Children</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Air,</hi> Element</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heir,</hi> of an Eſtate</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Appeal,</hi> to a higher Judge</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A peal,</hi> of Ringing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A pail,</hi> for Water</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A peel,</hi> for an Oven</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Peer,</hi> or Noble-man</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Pier,</hi> for Ships</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Appear,</hi> before one</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A pear,</hi> fruit</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aunt,</hi> a Father's Siſter</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ant,</hi> an Emmet</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Augur,</hi> a Wiſe man</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Augure,</hi> to bore with</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Attract,</hi> to draw</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Tract,</hi> or Diſcourſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Track,</hi> or Path</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Attribute,</hi> given, or appropriate</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Tribute,</hi> paid to a Prince</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſſent,</hi> to conſent</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A ſcent,</hi> or ſmell</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſcent,</hi> or going up</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sent,</hi> an errand</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Batcheler,</hi> or ſingle man</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Batchelor</hi> of Arts</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ball,</hi> to play with</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bale,</hi> or pack of Cards or Silk</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ball,</hi> a Company of Dancers</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bawl,</hi> or cry out</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baal,</hi> falſe God</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bark</hi> as a Dog</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bark</hi> of a Tree</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bark,</hi> or Barque, a little Veſſel</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bear,</hi> a Beaſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bear,</hi> or ſuffer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bare,</hi> naked</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bier,</hi> a Corps</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Beer,</hi> to drink</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Babble,</hi> talk Idlely</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baubles,</hi> trifles</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Babel,</hi> confuſion</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bow,</hi> to ſhoot</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bow,</hi> or bend</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bough</hi> of a Tree</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Boar,</hi> a Beaſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bore</hi> a hole</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Buy</hi> with money</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>By,</hi> the Prepoſition</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Buoy</hi> of a Ship</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Boy,</hi> or Child</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>By the Bie</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blew</hi> as the wind</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blue</hi> Colour</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brute</hi> or Beaſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bruit,</hi> or Rumor</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bread</hi> to eat</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Breed,</hi> ingender</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bred,</hi> taught</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brede</hi> of Silk or Worſted</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bowl,</hi> a Cup</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:21"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Boul,</hi> to play</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Breath,</hi> wind</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Breathe,</hi> to blow ſoftly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Beray,</hi> defile</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bewray,</hi> or diſcloſe.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cavalier,</hi> a Souldier</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caviller,</hi> Wrangler</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Council</hi> of the King</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Counſel,</hi> advice</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Councellor,</hi> privy Councellor</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Counſeller</hi> at Law</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Crew</hi> as a Cock</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Crue,</hi> a Company</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cenſer,</hi> for Inſence</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cenſor,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Officer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cenſure,</hi> or blame</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cymbal,</hi> an Inſtrument</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Symbol,</hi> a mark</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cittern</hi> for Muſick</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Citron,</hi> fruit</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Canon</hi> of the Church</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cannon,</hi> a Gunn</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cannion</hi> of breeches</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carret,</hi> a Root</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carract</hi> of Gold, whereof 18 make a <hi>Drachm.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dame,</hi> or Mother</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Damm,</hi> or bank</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Damn,</hi> condemn</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deer,</hi> Buck or Doe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dear,</hi> or coſtly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dear,</hi> moſt affectionate</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deſert,</hi> forſake</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Diſert</hi> after meat</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deſart,</hi> a Wilderneſs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Decent,</hi> orderly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deſcent,</hi> going down</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deſcent</hi> of an Eſtate</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Diſſent,</hi> diſagree</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Duke,</hi> a Title of Honor</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Duck,</hi> a Bird</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Demure,</hi> ſober, mild</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Demurr,</hi> doubt or delay</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dew</hi> on the Graſs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Due,</hi> owing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doe,</hi> Female-Deer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Do,</hi> or act</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dough,</hi> to make bread</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eminent,</hi> famous</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Imminent,</hi> at hand</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exerciſe</hi> or labor</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exorciſe,</hi> to Conjure</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Earneſt,</hi> Serious</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Earneſt,</hi> on a Bargain.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flie,</hi> to make haſte</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fly,</hi> as a Bird</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flie,</hi> an Inſect</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flea,</hi> or <hi>flegh</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fowl,</hi> Birds</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Foul,</hi> unclean</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flower</hi> in a Garden</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Flour</hi> of wheat</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Floor</hi> of a houſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fair,</hi> beautiful</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fare,</hi> entertainment</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Frieſe,</hi> courſe Cloath</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Freez,</hi> congeal</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fawn,</hi> or young Deer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Faun,</hi> or flatter</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Form,</hi> or ſhape</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourm,</hi> to ſit on</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Feign,</hi> falſify</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fain,</hi> deſire.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:21"/>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Guilt,</hi> offence</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gilt</hi> with Gold.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heir</hi> to an Eſtate</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Air,</hi> or wind</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hair</hi> of the Head</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hare,</hi> a Beaſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heart</hi> of any thing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hart,</hi> a great Deer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Head,</hi> or principal part</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heed,</hi> mind</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hoop</hi> of a Veſſel</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whoop</hi> or hollow</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hue,</hi> or Colour</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hue</hi> and Cry</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hew,</hi> or Cut</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugh,</hi> a name.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Inſight,</hi> skill</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Incite,</hi> ſtir-up</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ingenious,</hi> witty</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ingenuous,</hi> free, well-natur'd.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>J</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joynter,</hi> a Tool.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joynture,</hi> a portion.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>K</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kennel</hi> for Doggs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Channel,</hi> water paſſage.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Latine,</hi> a Language</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lattin,</hi> Tinn</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Looſe,</hi> or untie</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Loſe,</hi> or neglect</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leaſt,</hi> ſmalleſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leſt,</hi> a word of caution</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lettuce,</hi> an Herb</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Letice,</hi> a name</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lattice,</hi> Croſs barrs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leamons,</hi> Concubins</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Limons,</hi> fruit</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Luſter,</hi> a deſirer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Luſtre,</hi> ſhining.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Manor,</hi> Houſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Manure,</hi> to Till Ground</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Manner,</hi> faſhion</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mowe,</hi> Hay</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mow</hi> of Corn</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mortar,</hi> to build with</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Morter,</hi> to bruiſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Morning,</hi> Sun-riſing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mourning,</hi> Lamenting</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſsle,</hi> a Shell-fiſh</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſcles</hi> of a Man</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Martial,</hi> warlike</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marſhal,</hi> an Office</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mean,</hi> between two</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mien,</hi> viſage</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mean,</hi> poor</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mold,</hi> Earth</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mould,</hi> or frame.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nice,</hi> a Town</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Niece,</hi> or Brother's Daughter</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nice,</hi> or dainty</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> or mark</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Not</hi> at all.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:22"/>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>O,</hi> Exclamation!</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ow,</hi> a debt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oh,</hi> alas</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oar,</hi> or Gold duſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Or</hi> this, <hi>or</hi> that</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Oar,</hi> to Row</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Our,</hi> or <hi>ours</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hour</hi> of the day</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>One</hi> thing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>On,</hi> or <hi>upon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ordure,</hi> filth</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Order,</hi> or Commiſſion</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Off,</hi> or far away, out of</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of,</hi> concerning</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Only,</hi> ſo much</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Onely,</hi> ſingular.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pallet,</hi> to ly on</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Palat,</hi> or taſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pauſe,</hi> or ſtopp</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paws,</hi> or Feet</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perſon,</hi> or body</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Parſon,</hi> or Prieſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Precedent,</hi> forgoing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Preſident</hi> or Example</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Power</hi> or Authority</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pour</hi> out</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pail,</hi> for water</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peal,</hi> of Ringing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pale,</hi> ill-coloured</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pall,</hi> or Herſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prophet,</hi> or foreteller</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Profit,</hi> gain</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plane,</hi> a Field</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plain,</hi> ſmooth</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plan,</hi> or Model.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Q</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quarry</hi> of Stones</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quarrel</hi> of Glaſs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quack,</hi> or pretender</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quake,</hi> to ſhake.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Right,</hi> or Juſt</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rite,</hi> or Cuſtom</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wright,</hi> a Trade</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Write</hi> with a pen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reed,</hi> or Cane</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Read</hi> a Book</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Red</hi> Colour</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Retch</hi> out or ſtretch</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reach</hi> or fetch</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> a famous City</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> or wander</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Room,</hi> or Chamber</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reign</hi> as a King</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rein</hi> of a Bridle</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Row</hi> of Trees</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roe,</hi> or Deer</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Row</hi> a Boat.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sun,</hi> that ſhines</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Son</hi> of a Father</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Soon,</hi> quickly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Swound,</hi> or faint away</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sound,</hi> whole</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sealing</hi> of Letters</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ceiling</hi> of a Houſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stares,</hi> or looks earneſtly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stairs</hi> of a Houſe</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Some,</hi> or part</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sum</hi> of money</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Streight,</hi> even</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Strait,</hi> or narrow</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Straight,</hi> by and by</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Statue,</hi> or Image</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Statute,</hi> or Law</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Suit</hi> at Law</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:22"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sute</hi> of Cloathes</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sex,</hi> kind</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sects,</hi> factions</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Seller</hi> of Goods</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cellar</hi> for Wine</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Smock,</hi> a ſhift</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Smoak</hi> of fire.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Than,</hi> in Compariſon</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Then,</hi> at that time</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> man or thing</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thee,</hi> or thy ſelf</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Trade,</hi> or calling</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tread</hi> under foot</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tred</hi> as Birds</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>There</hi> in that place</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Their</hi> belonging to them</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To,</hi> or towards</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Toe</hi> of the foot</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tow,</hi> a Rope</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Too,</hi> alſo</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Two</hi> in number</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tenor</hi> in Muſic</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tennor,</hi> or form.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vain,</hi> Idle</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vein</hi> of blood</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vial,</hi> a little Glaſs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Viol,</hi> or Violin.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waſt</hi>-thou</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waſte,</hi> or ſpend</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waſte,</hi> Emply</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Waiſt,</hi> ones midle</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weight</hi> of Goods</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wait,</hi> attend</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wight,</hi> a man</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whether</hi> of the two</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Whither</hi> do you go</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Week</hi> 7 dayes</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wick</hi> of a Candle</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Walk</hi> in the fields</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wake,</hi> or <hi>awake</hi> from ſleep</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weak,</hi> not ſtrong.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>material words</hi> which are ſounded <hi>alike</hi> and ſpelt <hi>differently,</hi> and ought to be <hi>carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very <hi>convenient,</hi> that <hi>Youth</hi> be inſtructed to know theſe <hi>words</hi> from <hi>careful Tutors,</hi> who may ſet them a <hi>task</hi> to <hi>write over,</hi> and give a <hi>good Account</hi> of as <hi>many</hi> of them at a <hi>time</hi> as they are <hi>capable</hi> of: By which <hi>method</hi> and the <hi>other Rules</hi> in this Book <hi>preſcrib'd,</hi> I have taught <hi>young Perſons</hi> of <hi>both Sexes</hi> to <hi>ſpell En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> very well who knew <hi>nothing</hi> of <hi>Grammar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179339:23"/>
            <head>Engliſh Orthography. PART III. Containing <hi>directions</hi> for <hi>Writing</hi> and <hi>Folding</hi> of <hi>Letters Miſſive</hi> or <hi>Epiſtles.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of <hi>Letters</hi> in General.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>excellency</hi> and <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> of <hi>Letters</hi> are ſo <hi>univerſally</hi> known and acknowledged by perſons of <hi>all conditions</hi> and <hi>degrees,</hi> that an <hi>Eſſay</hi> in <hi>praiſe</hi> of them were as <hi>ridiculous</hi> as <hi>impertinent.</hi> All the <hi>world</hi> knows, how <hi>great</hi> their <hi>power</hi> is in the <hi>management</hi> of <hi>humane affairs</hi> both <hi>public</hi> and <hi>private:</hi> No <hi>man</hi> of <hi>ſenſe</hi> can be ignorant what <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> they have in the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of every <hi>particular State,</hi> how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> are <hi>diſcovered</hi> by them, and that they are the <hi>beſt Fountains</hi> out of which an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> can be <hi>drawn.</hi> 'Tis ſufficiently <hi>known,</hi> that by them not onely <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce</hi> are <hi>maintain'd</hi> in any <hi>one Teritory</hi> but <hi>Traffic</hi> is <hi>maintain'd</hi> and <hi>upheld</hi> through the whole <hi>habitable Earth;</hi> and in <hi>concluſion,</hi> all people <hi>agree,</hi> that they are the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſoul</hi> of <hi>Amity</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and that <hi>Communication</hi> by <hi>Letters</hi> doth almoſt <hi>contribute</hi> as much to the <hi>preſervation</hi> of <hi>civil Society</hi> amongſt men, as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>obligation</hi> of an <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, I ſhall not dwell upon theſe <hi>Topicks,</hi> it being my <hi>Deſign</hi> only ro propoſe ſome <hi>plain inſtructions</hi> for the right <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſealing</hi> and <hi>directing</hi> of ordinary <hi>miſſive Letters,</hi> and if my
<pb facs="tcp:179339:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:25"/> 
                  <hi>Rules</hi> ſometimes reach perſons of a <hi>higher Sphere,</hi> I intend them rather for <hi>Ornament</hi> and <hi>ſpeculation</hi> than for <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>Practice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is a <hi>great grace</hi> to <hi>Letters,</hi> to be <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>punctually</hi> written without <hi>blotts</hi> or <hi>confuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is ſufficient for <hi>men</hi> of <hi>Buſineſs</hi> to write <hi>Legibly</hi> and pretty <hi>free</hi> from <hi>Blotts,</hi> altho' it is very neceſſary for young <hi>Gentlemen, Ladies</hi> and Youth in General to write Letters as <hi>well</hi> as ever they <hi>can;</hi> for it looks like <hi>Idleneſs</hi> or <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> in them not to <hi>write</hi> their <hi>beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Petitions</hi> to <hi>Superiours</hi> muſt be written <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>well,</hi> ſince the <hi>very writing</hi> gives a high <hi>recommendation</hi> to them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>main Grace</hi> thereof conſiſts in <hi>ſpelling well,</hi> which hath been the <hi>deſign</hi> of the <hi>two former parts</hi> of this <hi>Book:</hi> nothing is more <hi>ridiculous,</hi> than Letters <hi>ill ſpelt,</hi> it arguing a <hi>mighty defect</hi> of <hi>Education:</hi> whereas on the contrary, to ſee a <hi>Letter</hi> from a <hi>Lady,</hi> or one who does <hi>not</hi> pretend to <hi>great Learning, well ſpelt,</hi> doth add a huge <hi>luſtre</hi> to their <hi>breeding,</hi> and is much <hi>prais'd</hi> and <hi>admired.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This,</hi> tho' it be very <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>good Education,</hi> and be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no <hi>ſmall part</hi> thereof, yet is generally <hi>too much neglected:</hi> but it is certainly a <hi>great Error</hi> in mens <hi>judgments;</hi> for a man that can <hi>ſpell well,</hi> is thought a <hi>Scholar,</hi> tho' he have but <hi>little Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Scholars</hi> who <hi>ſpell ill</hi> (as <hi>ſome</hi> do) are thought <hi>Ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it is not <hi>ſafe</hi> to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> ſo it is much more <hi>dangerous</hi> to <hi>committ</hi> any <hi>ſecret</hi> to <hi>paper,</hi> whether it concern the <hi>State,</hi> your <hi>Friend</hi> or your <hi>Self:</hi> for, according to the <hi>Poet,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vox edita perit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Litera Scripta manet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Words vaniſh ſoon, and vapour into Air,</l>
                     <l>While Letters on record ſtand freſh and fair.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Letters</hi> may be <hi>miſcarried;</hi> or they may be <hi>brought</hi> againſt you as a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> and in <hi>Law</hi> they are commonly accounted the <hi>beſt witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Promiſes</hi> in <hi>Letters</hi> are <hi>bonds,</hi> and therefore it is <hi>prudence</hi> to write nothing in a <hi>Letter,</hi> but what you <hi>needs muſt:</hi> how <hi>common</hi> is it to <hi>ſay,</hi> I have ſuch a <hi>mans Letter,</hi> can he <hi>deny</hi> his own <hi>hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179339:25"/>
                  <l>While Oaths and Evidence ſhall bear the Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Men of ſmall Conſcience little fear the Laws.</l>
                  <l>What Trade are you? a Witneſs, Sir draw near;</l>
                  <l>There's Coyn depoſe what I would have you ſwear.</l>
                  <l>But of deceit in <hi>Letters</hi> there's no fear.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of</hi> Superſcriptions, <hi>and</hi> Appellations <hi>in</hi> Letters.</head>
               <p>YOU are to <hi>conſider</hi> firſt, <hi>to whom</hi> you write, ſo that you may pay <hi>reſpect</hi> proper to the <hi>perſon,</hi> and give <hi>every man</hi> his <hi>due Title:</hi> and therefore you muſt take <hi>eſpecial care</hi> firſt of the <hi>Superſcription,</hi> which is <hi>two-fold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> lyeth <hi>within</hi> your Letter, and conſiſts in <hi>beginning</hi> it <hi>aright,</hi> that is, <hi>Appellations</hi> proper to <hi>perſons</hi> of all <hi>Ranks</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> amongſt men. The <hi>ſecond</hi> I <hi>ſhall</hi> conſider in its due <hi>place</hi> and <hi>time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For your <hi>better Inſtruction</hi> I will here ſet down ſome <hi>examples,</hi> how to <hi>begin</hi> Letters to perſons of all <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Conditions,</hi> by which you may <hi>ſee,</hi> what <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Deference</hi> is due to them. But when you write to <hi>perſons</hi> you <hi>know</hi> very well, or dare uſe <hi>familiarity</hi> with, you need not <hi>confine</hi> your ſelf to any <hi>Rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt <hi>familiars</hi> and <hi>equals</hi> it is common to uſe no <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions</hi> at the <hi>beginning</hi> but fall <hi>preſently</hi> to the <hi>buſineſs</hi> in hand, putting your <hi>Epithet</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> in a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> thus:
<q>
                     <l>Yeſterday <hi>(My Lord)</hi> I received yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ſhall not fail <hi>(Sir)</hi> to obey, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My urgent occaſions <hi>(Dear Father)</hi> require, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I came laſt night late from <hi>Windſor: (Dear Harry)</hi> come and let me ſee thee, <hi>&amp;c. and ſo on any exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Tho' it ſhows a <hi>profound reſpect</hi> to uſe <hi>Superſcriptions</hi> eſpecially to <hi>Superiours,</hi> yet I leave every one to his <hi>inclinations:</hi> it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient here to <hi>tell</hi> what is moſt <hi>proper</hi> on <hi>ſuch occaſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:179339:26"/>
                  <head>Forms <hi>of</hi> Superſcriptions <hi>or</hi> Appellations <hi>in</hi> Letters.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To the King:</hi> Sir <hi>(alias)</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Majeſty: <hi>or,</hi> Sacred Sir: <hi>or,</hi> Dread Sovereign.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To the Queen:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To the Princeſs:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Duke:</hi> My Lord, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gr.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Dutcheſs:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Grace,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Marqueſs:</hi> My Lord, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lordſhip.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Marqueſs's Lady:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> La<hi rend="sup">p</hi>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To an Earl:</hi> My Lord <hi>(aliàs)</hi> Right Hon<hi rend="sup">le</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To his Lady:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> Right Hon<hi rend="sup">le</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Viſcount:</hi> My Lord, <hi>or,</hi> Right Hon<hi rend="sup">le</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To his Lady:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> Right Hon<hi rend="sup">le</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Baron:</hi> My Lord, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lo<hi rend="sup">p</hi>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Baroneſs:</hi> Madam, <hi>or,</hi> May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> La<hi rend="sup">p</hi>,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To all Ladies, and Gentlewomen indifferently:</hi> Madam,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Baronet:</hi> Sir, <hi>aliàs,</hi> Right Worſhipful,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To a Knight:</hi> Sir, <hi>or,</hi> Right Worſhipful,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To an Eſquire:</hi> Sir, May it pleaſe Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Worſhip,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To any Gentleman:</hi> Sir, <hi>or,</hi> Much Honoured,</item>
               </list>
               <p>¶ At the <hi>end</hi> of your <hi>Letter,</hi> Repeat the ſame again towards the <hi>left hand,</hi> thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Graces moſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:26"/>
               <p>Tho' (as I ſaid <hi>before</hi>) amongſt <hi>equals</hi> and <hi>familiars</hi> you may uſe your <hi>diſcretion</hi> without <hi>Ceremony,</hi> (which is <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with <hi>common Affairs</hi>) yet it is <hi>convenient</hi> to give <hi>Superiours</hi> rather <hi>too much</hi> than <hi>too little Reſpect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeveral <hi>Degrees</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nobility</hi> are alſo <hi>differenced</hi> and <hi>Diſtinguiſhed</hi> one from another by their <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Enſigns</hi> of <hi>Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>A <hi>Duke</hi> hath the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and, when he is <hi>writt-to,</hi> may be ſtil'd, <hi>Moſt High, Potent and Noble Prince.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Marqueſs: Moſt Noble and Potent Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An Earl <hi>the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Viſcount, <hi>Right Potent and Noble Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Baron, <hi>Right Noble Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>When you write to a <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Quality,</hi> you are to leave a <hi>great diſtance</hi> between the <hi>Superſcription</hi> or <hi>firſt line</hi> and the <hi>ſecond line</hi> or beginning of your <hi>Letter:</hi> for, the <hi>greater diſtance</hi> you leave the <hi>greater reſpect</hi> you ſhow; as you may ſee by the <hi>Examples</hi> of <hi>Letters,</hi> which I ſhall have <hi>occaſion</hi> to <hi>ſhow</hi> in the <hi>laſt Chapter</hi> of this <hi>brief Treatiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you write to your <hi>familiars,</hi> near <hi>Relations</hi> or thoſe you are very <hi>intimate</hi> with, <hi>great</hi> and <hi>lofty Complements</hi> are not ſo well <hi>taken,</hi> which ſeem to <hi>proceed</hi> rather from <hi>Affectation</hi> than a man's <hi>natural Addreſs:</hi> ſo that the <hi>beſt way</hi> is to uſe your own <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar</hi> and <hi>uſual Expreſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Title of <hi>Sir,</hi> or <hi>Maſter</hi> is generally given to <hi>all Gentlemen</hi> or <hi>others</hi> (tho' ſometimes <hi>mean Perſons</hi>) ſo the Title of <hi>Madam</hi> or <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> is univerſally beſtow'd upon <hi>all Gentlewomen</hi> and others (provided they be not of very <hi>Low</hi> and <hi>baſe Condition:</hi>) ſuch is the <hi>frank</hi> and <hi>Bountiful</hi> courteſy of <hi>England</hi> above other <hi>Nations</hi> to the <hi>Female Sex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Title of <hi>Lady</hi> is not only attributed to all the <hi>Nobility,</hi> but likewiſe to <hi>others</hi> of <hi>lower Rank,</hi> that come under the <hi>notion</hi> of <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> (who upon that Account are much in <hi>Arrears</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Civility</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> for them) both in <hi>writing</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> altho' in <hi>Law</hi> it is not <hi>allowed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To thoſe <hi>A-kin</hi> to us it is uſual to aſcribe their <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:</hi> as <hi>Dear Father,</hi> or <hi>Mother, Honoured <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> or <hi>Aunt, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Brother,</hi> or <hi>Siſter,</hi> or <hi>Couſin:</hi> or in what <hi>other Epithets</hi> you pleaſe to expreſs your <hi>affection.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:179339:27"/>
               <p>This is indeed the <hi>common practice</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but it would be interpreted great <hi>arrogancy</hi> or <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> in all other the moſt <hi>polite</hi> and <hi>civiliz'd Nations:</hi> for no man ought to mention <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's relation</hi> to him, but when it muſt be <hi>acknowledged</hi> an <hi>honour</hi> to the perſon <hi>addreſs'd</hi> to.</p>
               <p>When Perſons, who are of <hi>near kindred</hi> write one to another, the Perſon of <hi>greater Quality</hi> may expreſs the <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>kindred</hi> in the <hi>beginning,</hi> but it better becomes thoſe of a <hi>meaner Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> to do it at the <hi>latter end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if your <hi>Condition</hi> be not <hi>conformable,</hi> it is wiſdom to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal</hi> any <hi>pretence</hi> to <hi>great men,</hi> or to the <hi>rich;</hi> it being only <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> for them to <hi>own</hi> you; and if you <hi>truely deſerve,</hi> they <hi>will.</hi> In men who are <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to live <hi>below</hi> their <hi>birth,</hi> it is great <hi>diſcretion</hi> to wave <hi>pretenſions</hi> to <hi>great things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis generally obſerv'd, that <hi>true Gentlemen</hi> are <hi>ſilent</hi> on ſuch occaſions; none but <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>mean-born</hi> pretenders to <hi>Gentility</hi> impoſe their <hi>Extravagant Brags</hi> on <hi>Company,</hi> and for their <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous vanity</hi> are ſtill <hi>leſs eſteem'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>"Firſt, God's Commands, your Parents next obey:</l>
                  <l>"A thouſand Snares, Pride, Luſt and Avarice lay.</l>
                  <l>Pretend not blood, or kindred to the Great,</l>
                  <l>But when the Truth is backt with an Eſtate:</l>
                  <l>Who would not ſmile to hear a Servile Clown,</l>
                  <l>Pretending kindred, honour and renown?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Proems, or Introductions to Letters.</head>
               <p>IN the <hi>beginning</hi> it is <hi>cuſtomary</hi> and <hi>handſome</hi> to make ſome <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble</hi> or <hi>Introduction,</hi> which may uſher in the <hi>main ſubject-matter:</hi> and when this is done, your greateſt <hi>trouble</hi> is <hi>paſt;</hi> for, then your <hi>thoughts,</hi> which were before <hi>bounded</hi> up by themſelves, run <hi>fluently,</hi> like an <hi>Exuberant River,</hi> that has found a <hi>new paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage</hi> for its <hi>waters,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:179339:27"/>
               <p>I ſhall here for your <hi>farther direction</hi> ſet down <hi>Forms</hi> to <hi>begin Letters</hi> withal, uſed amongſt <hi>all degrees,</hi> which you may make <hi>uſe</hi> of at your <hi>pleaſure:</hi> and, though you are not <hi>confin'd</hi> to <hi>my words,</hi> yet you may by reading <hi>theſe,</hi> be enabled to expreſs your mind ſomething <hi>better</hi> according to your own <hi>particular fancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>Secretaries</hi> ſometimes uſe <hi>this way</hi> of <hi>beginning,</hi> though they never <hi>tie</hi> themſelves up to <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> or <hi>Rules:</hi> but it is very <hi>convenient,</hi> that thoſe of <hi>meaner quality</hi> ſhould uſe ſuch eſpecially to <hi>Superiours.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>Forms of beginning Letters.</head>
                  <item>YOU have oblig'd me ſo much, that I am wholly at your command, and therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There is nothing in my power, but you may very freely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which is but the leaſt of my duty; ſeeing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I cannot think of your goodneſs without admiration, ſeeing I am ſo far below your notice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I do acknowledge it is my duty to receive your commands with chearfulneſs, and, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your merits have rendred your condition ſo conſiderable, that you are the comfort and refuge of your Friends: wherefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I eſteem my ſelf moſt happy in your correſpondency, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place and length of time ſhall never alter me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your abſence is very grievous to me; ſo that either return quickly, or write oftner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If it were as eaſie to convince, as to accuſe, men would be in a much better ſtate, and, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If you expect thanks ſuteable to your favours, I beſeech you teach me in what manner to return them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The news of your good Fortune was no ſmall joy to me.</item>
                  <item>If wiſhes would do, you may eaſily conjecture what I would do.</item>
                  <item>Having the opportunity of this Bearer, I could not omit to tell you, that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Yours I r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eived Yeſterday of the 13th inſtant, wherein you are pleaſed to acquaint me, that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All the News here in Town at preſent, is that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your friendſhip is ſo neceſſary to me, that all my other happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would be imperfect without it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Yours I received with great ſatisfaction, and I return you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thanks for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:179339:28"/>
                  <item>The obligations you daily lay upon me, do very much ſurprize me, becauſe I cannot find any occaſion to expreſs my Gratitude.</item>
                  <item>I received your kind Token by your good Friend <hi>J. R.</hi> for which I return you my humble thanks.</item>
                  <item>If you expect Complements from me, you may chance to be diſappointed; for I am a profeſſed Enemy to them, being a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile way of telling a Ly.</item>
                  <item>Though you are out of my reach, yet you are not out of my remembrance: for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I eſteem my ſelf very fortunate, becauſe I retain your good opinion, and, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ſame obſervance that a Father may claim from a Child, your kindneſs hath oblig'd me to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If you think me unworthy of an anſwer, pray ſend me my own Letter back again.</item>
                  <item>My laſt to you was of the 14th of <hi>December</hi> laſt, but having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no Anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I preſume my laſt came ſafe to your hands, and therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Since you have provok'd me, I muſt make bold to tell you, that Friends and Acquaintance wou'd not know what to do with themſelves, if it were not for this bleſſed Art of Writing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I no ſooner received yours, but, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If I had not a great eſteem of your Sincerity, I could hardly digeſt what I am told, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Were I as able as I am willing, words ſhould ſoon be turn'd into actions.</item>
                  <item>It is gratitude to receive a good turn civilly, to retain it in mind, and acknowledge it, but moſt of all to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite it: and therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You need not requeſt, but command me, ſince by obliging you I content my ſelf.</item>
                  <item>If Letters were as ſwift as wiſhes, You may aſſure your ſelf, that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You need not complement at this rate: for your favour and correſpondence is ſufficient reward for my ſmall endeavours.</item>
                  <item>I need not be put in mind of your Affairs: Your generous Actions will never be blotted out of my memory, nor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I hereby ſend you my due and humble thanks for all your kindneſſes, but eſpecially for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>According to the advice you ſent me in your laſt, I, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Life is a load without Friendſhip, and therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>By this I ſee, that honour and preferment are rather the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Flattery and Intereſt than of Vertue.</item>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:179339:28"/>
                  <item>You have given ſuch demonſtrations of your goodneſs, that it would be ingrateful to queſtion it.</item>
                  <item>Complements will not paſs among thoſe who can diſcern re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance from reality: upon which account, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Since I had the honour of your Acquaintance, I have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently received teſtimonies of your Love, and particularly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Court now affords little news, but, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gratitude is the poor mans vertue; and ſeeing I cannot be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral, I will endeavour not to be unmindful of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your favours to me are ſo far above my merits, that they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs my gratitude.</item>
                  <item>According to my promiſe and that portion of obedience I ow your Commands, I here renew my proteſtations (after having rendred you many thanks for your laſt, and for the good news therein) that I will certainly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Next under God, I look upon you to be my beſt Friend upon Earth: I have found it ſo, and I will evermore own it.</item>
                  <item>You have been ready on all occaſions to oblige me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Having <hi>once</hi> begun your <hi>Epiſtle</hi> with <hi>theſe</hi> or <hi>ſuch like Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> you may <hi>proceed</hi> according to your <hi>occaſions,</hi> for <hi>that which is once well begun, is half ended:</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dimidium facti, qui benè coepit, habet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He hath his work half done,</l>
                  <l>That hath it well begun.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the <hi>main Subject,</hi> and of the <hi>Concluſions</hi> of <hi>Letters</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFTER you have <hi>begun</hi> your <hi>Letters</hi> with ſome ſuch Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as I have mention'd in the <hi>laſt Chapter,</hi> according to the <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>perſon,</hi> or your own <hi>diſcretion,</hi> you may <hi>proceed</hi> and <hi>declare</hi> your <hi>mind</hi> in your own <hi>natural terms,</hi> uſing <hi>ſhort periods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shun <hi>vain Repetitions</hi> and <hi>Cramp words;</hi> the <hi>eaſieſt</hi> and <hi>plaineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſtyle being moſt <hi>uſual</hi> and <hi>commendable,</hi> as it is the <hi>ſtyle</hi> of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:179339:29"/> 
                  <hi>Languages</hi> and <hi>Converſation:</hi> Wherefore let it be <hi>furniſh'd</hi> and <hi>compacted</hi> with the beſt, <hi>choiceſt</hi> and moſt <hi>familiar words,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther going <hi>before,</hi> or coming <hi>after</hi> the <hi>uſe</hi> of the <hi>age</hi> you live in, nor <hi>conſiſting</hi> of either <hi>antiquated</hi> or ſuch new <hi>upſtart words,</hi> as our <hi>Pamphlets</hi> and <hi>Novels</hi> daily introduce.</p>
               <p>Avoid all <hi>obſcurity</hi> in expreſſing your ſelf in <hi>ſuch terms,</hi> as men ſhall rather <hi>admire</hi> than <hi>underſtand. Choice</hi> Sentences and <hi>wittie</hi> Expreſſions being the beſt, <hi>fitted</hi> to the <hi>humour</hi> and <hi>capacity</hi> of the <hi>Perſon</hi> you write unto. You are to <hi>conſider,</hi> what will be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>beſt attention,</hi> and next what will leave the <hi>ſweeteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>impreſſion</hi> in the <hi>mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brevitie</hi> is a great <hi>grace</hi> to Letters: you are therefore to <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> your ſelf, and <hi>ſtudy</hi> to <hi>expreſs</hi> your mind in the moſt <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant Engliſh</hi> words you can think of, and <hi>convenient</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>buſineſs</hi> in <hi>hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This you may do by avoiding <hi>Idle Complements, Prefaces</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> keeping cloſe to the <hi>matter</hi> before you without <hi>vain circuits</hi> of <hi>figures, digreſſions, conjunctions</hi> and <hi>flouriſhes</hi> of preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Rhetoric.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you write to your <hi>Superiour,</hi> you are bound to conſider in him theſe things; <hi>firſt,</hi> your <hi>intereſt</hi> in him, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> his <hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi> (for all men are not alike <hi>gifted) thirdly,</hi> his <hi>leaſure.</hi> You are <hi>oblig'd</hi> to the greater <hi>brevity,</hi> as his <hi>place</hi> is of greater <hi>concern,</hi> or care: For <hi>long</hi> and <hi>tedious</hi> Letters are very <hi>troubleſome</hi> to <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> in a thing brings <hi>perfection,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be <hi>ready</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> you muſt write <hi>often.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> when you have ſaid <hi>all</hi> you have to ſay, <hi>conclude</hi> your Letter with ſome ſhort <hi>aſſeveration</hi> of your <hi>affections</hi> in the <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or the <hi>like words,</hi> not uſing always the <hi>ſame words,</hi> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Forms <hi>of</hi> concluding <hi>Letters.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>IF I ſhall prove ſo fortunate, as to be remembred by you, it will be a great obligation upon Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>This great kindneſs ſhall never be forgotten by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Such great favours as I have received can never be forgotten but with ingratitude by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You have conferr'd ſuch obligations undeſervedly upon me; that, ſince they can never be requited, they ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:179339:29"/>
                  <item>There is nothing I deſire more than to be continued Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There is nothing I value more than your favour, ſo that I hope nothing can perſwade you that I am not Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That God would bleſs you with all earthly bleſſings, and give you contentment here and hereafter, ſhall be the conſtant prayers of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When I think on your favours, and my deſerts, I cannot but admire your goodneſs, and ſhall on all occaſions continue Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You have ſo much obliged me, that upon all occaſions I muſt acknowledge my ſelf Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In the mean time, remember, that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I ſhall ſooner forget my own name, than the obligation to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There is nothing more pleaſing to me than to have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſhew how much I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I humbly beg, that you would be pleas'd to own me to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I muſt repay all your kindneſs with the uncurrent Coin of thanks, being all the Treaſure of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your favours have ſo much ſurpriz'd me, that I want words to expreſs, how much I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I am ſo far below your notice, that I admire your goodneſs the more in beſtowing your favours ſo liberally on a perſon, who was oblig'd to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your favours are ſo far beyond my merits, that they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether above my gratitude: it lies onely in my power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In doing this, you will confer an obligation beyond expreſſion upon Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And this I deſire may be regiſtred amongſt the reſt of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It is my ambition to be continued Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I know nothing more at preſent, but that I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I eſteem my ſelf fortunate in having this opportunity to ſhew, that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If this can pleaſure you, you ſhall upon all occaſions be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It is honour enough for me to be continued Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your Countenance is no ſmall encouragement to Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I am very proud of your acquaintance; and if you will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me with the continuance thereof, you will oblige Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:179339:30"/>
                  <item>I hope you will pardon my failings, your goodneſs being as great as my deſire to continue Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I aſſure you, no man living can be more, than I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Whatever happens, I am reſolv'd to continue Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I cannot either be melancholy or miſerable, ſo long as you are pleas'd to continue me in quality of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I wiſh I could be ſo fortunate, as to tell you face to face how much I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pray pardon my tedious Expreſſions, ſince I cannot refrain to repeat the many obligations you have put upon Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I ſhall be ready upon all occaſions to diſcharge that duty, which your kindneſs requires from Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If you will grant this my humble requeſt, it will be a great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I wiſh I had any ſuitable occaſion to demonſtrate how much I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I hope you will accept of this imperfect acknowledgment, till I am able to give a perfect teſtimony, that I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There are many more able, but none more willing than, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If I had power equivalent to my will, there ſhould be no man more ſerviceable than, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I ſo much honour you, that it is impoſſible you ſhould want perfect happineſs, were it in the power of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I wiſh it were in my power to make my Actions demonſtrate, how much I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Were my Actions as eaſie to me as words, I ſhould ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If in my imployment I could be any ways ſerviceable to you, it is my intereſt to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The great obligations I have from you have engag'd me to live and die Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>My living depends altogether on my liberty, and ſo for both I am oblig'd to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>This with my humble ſervice is all from, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Live pleaſantly, baniſh melancholy, and remember Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Humbly begging the continuance of your kindneſs, I reſt Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pray remember me kindly to all friends; and when you can ſpare time, beſtow a thought committed to a ſmall piece of paper upon Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>This with my kind reſpects to you and your worthy Lady, and my ſervice where it is due, is all from Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:30"/>
                  <item>So may all health and happineſs attend you, according to the wiſhes of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Believe it, <hi>Sir,</hi> any Commands from you ſhall be welcome to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When any thing of moment or importance fals out, I hope you will think upon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fare well, <hi>kind Sir,</hi> the continuance of your correſpondence in pure love and friendſhip will be very acceptable to Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That you may have a proſperous Journey, and a happy return, ſhall be the conſtant prayers of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Many things are changeable, but I am ſtill Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If you think any thing can alter my affection, you are much miſtaken in Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I ſhall ever count my ſelf happy, ſo long as you are pleaſed to continue me Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You need not put me in mind of your affairs here, ſince I am reſolved to make no difference between your intereſt, and that of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In this I ſhall not implore your belief, deſiring to let you ſee by effects rather than words, that I am without complement Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You may have more powerfull and conſiderable Servants, but none more than my ſelf Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Keep your Complements for Strangers, and remember to uſe more familiarity with Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I do not queſtion your power or your will, which makes me believe you will comply with this occaſion to oblige Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If I had as often occaſions to ſerve you, as I have to write, my Actions ſhould declare, that I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Return your anſwer quickly, if you love the quiet of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If I thought my abſence could occaſion your diſqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, or my preſence were neceſſary to your ſervice, you ſhould ſee by my ſpeedy return, how much I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The unwelcome news of your ſickneſs is the greateſt grief could happen to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In doing ſo, you will confer an obligation beyond expreſſion upon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your countenance is no ſmall encouragement to Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If Idle Reports can diſguſt you, it ſhall never alter Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>It lies not in the power of either foes or flattery, to alter my reſolution to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>If you doubt of the truth of my Inclinations to ſerve you, your Commands will make the beſt proof that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:31"/>
                  <item>I can never think of your favours, but it renews the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my engagements to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There is nothing I hate more than ingratitude; yet I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be called ingrateful when I ſhall ceaſe to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I ſhall never prove ſo ungrateful as not to confeſs my ſelf Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When the world ſpeaks worſt of me, it is ſome comfort to my Conſcience that I find not my ſelf ſo vicious as to forget what obligations I have to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I beg your acceptance of this teſtimony of my gratitude and my earneſt deſires to deſerve the name of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Though there is a deficiency in my expreſſions, yet there is none in my inclinations to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I take it as a great favour that you employ me in any thing that may conduce to your contentment, becauſe I am very ambitious to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That God would ſend you a happy Journey, and a ſafe return, ſhall be the conſtant prayers of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Since nothing elſe will ſerve you, I kiſs your hands, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelf yours as you deſerve, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I will conclude at preſent, but never ceaſe to be Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I humbly deſire the help of your prayers for the proſperity of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>When you pray, I hope you will always remember Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And I hope the God of Heaven will proſper the endeavours of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You may freely command whatſoever lies in the power of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In which hopes I reſt Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I am fully convinc'd of your love by its good effects towards Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I would do a thouſand times more for your ſake if it were in the power of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>This I can aſſure you of, and likewiſe that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>I have often told you by word of mouth that I love you, yet my Pen ſhall once more aſſure you that I am Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Your deſires have always been lookt upon by me as commands, which ſhall be ever valued by Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>We both ſhall be much oblig'd to you, he as your Petitioner, and I as Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>God Almighty preſerve all good Chriſtians from ſuch things, eſpecially your ſelf, and Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:31"/>
                  <item>God preſerve his Majeſty, and the Royal Family, The Church, your friends and mine; this is the daily prayers of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All this ſhall be aſſerted by Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>You ſhall find me upon all opportunities Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All theſe are but the leaſt part of the duty of Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Then you are to ſubſcribe your Letters with this or the like tender of your Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SIR, Your moſt humble and obedient Servant</hi> J. C.</p>
               <p>This muſt always be done according to the quality, condition, or relation of the Perſon to whom you write: but herein you may uſe your own diſcretion, giving every man his due.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of dating, folding and ſealing of Letters.</head>
               <p>WHEN you have thus concluded your Letter, read it all over, and what hath either eſcap'd your mind or pen correct prudently.</p>
               <p>Then date your Letter at the end towards the left hand when you write to your Superiour; otherwiſe you may date it at the top: but fancy may take more place herein than judgment.</p>
               <p>It is a Cuſtom amongſt Perſons of quality to leave no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: which though it be a cuſtom, for which no convincing Reaſon can be aſſign'd, yet ſeeing they uſe it, it is not amiſs to uſe it to them.</p>
               <p>But in Letters of Buſineſs a broad margent is very proper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe things may be omitted, and the Perſon to whom you write, may mark every paſſage, the better to anſwer.</p>
               <p>In folding or making up Letters, many affect odd fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal forms, troubleſome to themſelves, and Readers, being fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently torn in the opening; wherefore I would recommend the plaineſt and the eaſieſt way, which amongſt all Secretaries, and men of parts, is the Cuſtom.</p>
               <p>Next you come to ſealing, which is either with Wax, or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, The firſt is eſteem'd moſt reſpectful, though the later is
<pb facs="tcp:179339:32"/> tolerable, Wafers being ready on all occaſions without farther trouble.</p>
               <p>To ſeal with Wax, and make a good and clear Impreſſion, having lighted your Wax, drop on the Paper enough to fill the Seal, then ſtir it about with the ſtick of Wax untill the black, or ſmoak of the Candle be gon. Then clap on the Seal with a ſudden jerk, holding it without moving till the Wax be cold, and you ſhall be ſure to have the full and clear Impreſſion of your Seal to great perfection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of External Superſcriptions or Directions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE other Superſcription or direction is on the Back of your Letter, which muſt be writ very legible, and muſt contain the name and title of him to whom you write, with the exact place of his reſidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As I ſaid before it is improper to expreſs any degree of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred on the back of a Letter; it concerns not the Bearer what alliance or relation is between the Writer and Receiver, no more than the ſuperfluous Addition of haſte and ſpeed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes ſwiftneſs to the Poſt-boys Horſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For your better information I ſhall here ſubjoin Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Directions to Perſons of all Ranks and Degrees, as Firſt,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>To the King: <hi>(alias)</hi> To the King's moſt Excellent Maj<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, To the Sacred Majeſty of <hi>James</hi> the Second.</item>
                     <item>To the Queen: To the Queen's moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</item>
                     <item>To the Prince: <hi>alias,</hi> To his Royal Highneſs.</item>
                     <item>To the Princeſs: To her R. H.</item>
                     <item>To his Grace the Lord A. B. of <hi>Cant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To his Grace the Lord A. B. of <hi>York.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>You may add, To the Moſt Reverend Father in God: if you pleaſe.</item>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:179339:32"/>
                     <item>To the Right Reverend Father in God, The Lord Biſhop of <hi>L.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>All Biſhops are ſo ſtiled.</item>
                     <item>All the Inferiour Clergy: To the Reverend Dr. <hi>A. B.</hi> with the Title of his Preferment, or Dignity.</item>
                     <item>To his Grace the D. of <hi>N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable the Marq. of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Lord <hi>M.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>M.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable the Lord Viſcount of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>All Sons of the Nobility are Honourable, and ought to be addreſt to with great Reſpect.</item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>John W.</hi> Knight and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet.</item>
                     <item>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>T. M.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To Sir <hi>J. L.</hi> Theſe.</item>
                     <item>Every Privy Councellour is Right Honourable.</item>
                     <item>To his Excellency <hi>L. E.</hi> of <hi>F.</hi> Captain General of his Majeſtie's Forces.</item>
                     <item>Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland:</hi> His Excellency.</item>
                     <item>Ambaſſadours: Excellency.</item>
                     <item>To the Honourable Collonel <hi>W.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Worſhipful <hi>T. M.</hi> Eſq;</item>
                     <item>To Mr. <hi>J. F.</hi> Theſe.</item>
                     <item>To the Right Honourable <hi>J. J.</hi> Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To the Right Worſhipful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sheriff of <hi>L.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>All thoſe that have been Lord Mayors of <hi>London</hi> are Honourable.</item>
                     <item>To the Worſhipful Alderman <hi>A. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>All men who have been Mayors of Towns, Maſters of Companies or Corporations by the King's Charter or Commiſſion, are afterwards Eſquires.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179339:33"/>
               <p>It is uſual when we write to Perſons of quality to put a cover on the Letter: that is a piece of clean paper put about it and ſeal'd, which is a token of great reſpect.</p>
               <p>When you write to any Superiour, it ought to be done with very great reſpect and honour; here too much is better than too little. It is not every one that knows what is juſtly due to all degrees amongſt men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Examples of Letters.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as Precepts without Examples are generally to little purpoſe, I think it fitting here to add a ſmall Packet of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which may be a kind of Rule of direction as to the intire compoſition and frame of Letters. And firſt,</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter of Complement and Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to a Great Souldier return'd from the Wars againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IF the general Joy which is now diffuſed through the hearts of all good Chriſtians, honeſt-minded men and Loyal Subjects in Chriſtendom, beſides the particular obligations I have received from Your Lordſhip had not an equal (or perhaps a greater) influence upon me than upon any man elſe, I ſhould not have preſum'd to have troubled Your Lordſhip at this time of publick rejoycing, but that I think by crowding in with the univerſal
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179339:33"/> Acclamations of Chriſtendom, and in particular theſe Nations at once to commit and attone for the ſame Crime: for, my Lord, give me leave to ſay this is intended not ſo much to congratulate Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips fortunate and honourable Eſcape out of thoſe many and glorious hazards, which a reſolute and undaunted Valour in conjunction with a moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Honour and Loyalty engag'd You in, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud to our ſelves the happineſs we are like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy both in Church and State, occaſioned by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of the Enemies both of God and Man, the Infidels and Rebels; and to give Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more particularly Your due, who being more ambitious of Honour than of Life, who ſo nobly ventur'd Yours in theſe Heroick Exploits for the Honour of Your Prince, and the Intereſt of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity. The Hiſtorians of this Age will not be ſo ungratefull as to forget to deliver down to Poſterity this Illuſtrious Subject, where by your War-like Atchievements you ſtrive to demonſtrate the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Anceſtours, rather than by a vain and unperforming Muſter of their old Charters, Patents and Commiſſions: thus, My Lord, You know that by Arms Honour was firſt acquir'd, which makes me thus aſſume the boldneſs of this imperfect and ſhort attempt in Your Lordſhip's Encomium, not doubting Your pardon; which I have the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon to hope for, becauſe it is free from two Vices equally hateful to men of Arms, I mean Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and long Harangues.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:179339:34"/>
                     <head>A Letter of Commerce to Mr. <hi>D.</hi> Bookseller at <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Mr.</hi> D.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOurs I received, and according to your deſire herewith ſend you ſix of <hi>Grew</hi>'s <hi>Muſaeum's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis Societatis;</hi> I am extreamly glad to hear they ſell ſo well at that great <hi>Muſaeum</hi> of all <hi>England,</hi> which as it is the beſt Judge, ſo it is the beſt uſer and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory of ſuch Books. I have nothing to add at preſent, but that your returns are accepted of by,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Friend to ſerve you</hi> Joſ. Hindmarſh.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Love Letter to <hi>Silvia.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SInce Madam <hi>Smith</hi> has been ſo kind as to take upon her the charge of this Letter, I have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured now to write to you. I know very well, I ought to do no ſuch thing, and by right, I ſhould dream as little of You as you have thought of me theſe three weeks. I went to look out for You with great earneſtneſs at my Lady — Houſe, but <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> was not there nor any where elſe that I could hear of; ſo that I was forc'd to leave— without bidding You adieu: but tho' I departed without ſeeing You, yet I ſee you but too plainly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179339:34"/> every day. What? cannot threeſcore miles ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate You from a Heart that you take ſo little care of; and cannot this Heart, that is ſo indifferent to You, divide it ſelf from You? You have made it inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to all the pleaſures that here in this Town croud about it, to feel only its melancholy perplexities: they are its only imployment at preſent. Now I could wiſh You would ſomewhat qualifie them by a Letter or ſo: But now! do not write to me, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with You is very dangerous, I am but too well acquainted what ſtyle You write in, and Your Letters would complete my ruine, when I ſhould read over a hundred and a hundred times the Characters of a hand, that has ſo much wit at its fingers ends; however, I lodge now at — and this is my direction: Let what will happen, I will not tell You by retail all that I have endured ſince my departure with the greateſt long-ſuffering in the world; why ſhould Your Idea thus inceſſantly haunt me every where; and is not <hi>London</hi> a place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge againſt that charming Image that always fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows me? I could tell you a hundred things more, but I am afraid I have ſaid too much already: I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an anſwer with ſuch an impatience as I wiſh You could conceive. Think ſometimes of a man that thinks of nothing but you, and be ſo gracious as to give me ſome hopes that You are pleaſed to accept of me as,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                        <signed>Your moſt devoted humble Servant <hi>J. R.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:179339:35"/>
               <p>¶ Every Subject has a diſtinct ſort of ſtyle and Character, as may be ſeen by theſe <hi>three</hi> Letters: The firſt is in a pompous and high way, moſt becoming the Souldier. The ſecond is conciſe and ſhort in its diction: ſaying no more than what is purely for bargain and intereſt. The third is a paſſionate and uncertain way of expreſſing the mind, like the fond ſouls of Lovers, which bear much reſemblance to the Sea, from whence Love is ſaid to have ſprung.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are arrived to any improvement by frequent wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Letters, will eaſily ſee theſe various differences, and will take care to accommodate themſelves accordingly, eſpecially when they have once come to ſome moderate knowledge in buſineſs and converſation; but for the younger and unexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd I ſhall add a few examples more.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter to perſwade a Friend to Marry.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Harry,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AS thy Friend (and I am ſatisfied you think me ſo) I adviſe you as you love your intereſt to marry. Age comes on apace, therefore change that melancholy and uncertain ſtate wherein you now live, for one infinitely more delightful: the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of which condition you have often admired in me by your own words, <hi>That when my one half was abroad the other was at home.</hi> The pleaſing converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Female Sex, which averts dull and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy thoughts, is moſt certainly charming; and beſides, your daily expences now would go a great way in a Family, I adviſe you alſo not to ſet your thoughts ſo much on <hi>riches</hi> as on a good humour: If you find a vertuous good natur'd woman, edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by worthy Parents, whom you can truly love, make no more delay (begging God's aſſiſtance in ſuch a great concern) If you chance to marry where
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179339:35"/> you do not love, you will love where you cannot marry. I have ſeen pretty lines on that Subject which I recommend to your peruſal, that is,
<q>
                           <l>Who makes the object of his fancy Gold,</l>
                           <l>Grows cold in fancy when the money's told.</l>
                           <l>And ſhe who feigns to love to live a Lady,</l>
                           <l>Is Honour's Faun, I know not what ſhe may be.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>To which I ſubjoin four more thus,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But thoſe whom Love and Honour join in one;</l>
                        <l>Will love each other when the Money's gone</l>
                        <l>With mutual kindneſs labouring both for life,</l>
                        <l>Free from all grudging diſcontent or ſtrife.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Be no more faint-hearted, but nobly venture, and mind not the ſilly morals which old muſty Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and bad Husbands commonly have againſt that honourable condition. This, dear <hi>H.</hi> I adviſe from my own experience, becauſe I enjoy all the comforts marriage can afford; think on this, and ſlight not this cordial advice of,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt affectionate Friend, <hi>J. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>An Anſwer to the foregoing Letter.</head>
                     <p>THere is nothing earthly (dear <hi>Jack</hi>) I value more ſacred than Friendſhip, and none ſo dearly as yours. I thank you heartily that you would be ſo free with me: And to let you ſee that I have both courage to venture and faith to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lieve it my
<pb facs="tcp:179339:36"/> beſt courſe, as I have not (on that account) refuſed any reaſonable propoſals, ſo neither ſhall I reject to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable profers. I muſt confeſs I am afraid to meet with a piece of Extravagancy and Ill-nature, which would as certainly make me miſerable as the other you propound would make me happy. That I ought to marry for Love more than Money you know I am convinc'd it is my Intereſt, and I not only am of the opinion of your firſt <hi>four</hi> Lines, but alſo join with yours in the other; and were I ſure to find ſuch happineſs in a married life as I have found deſcribed in another Poem on that Subject, I ſhould not delay. The fancy is this,
<q>
                           <l>They were ſo one that none could truly ſay</l>
                           <l>Which of them rul'd or whether did obey;</l>
                           <l>He rul'd becauſe ſhe would obey, and ſhe</l>
                           <l>In ſo obeying rul'd as well as he:</l>
                           <l>What pleas'd him beſt it need no other cauſe</l>
                           <l>To pleaſe her too but only his applauſe.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Is there any man living that does not admire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and mutual affection between Man and Wife, the greateſt comfort of humane life? and were I ſure to find ſuch a Wife as God hath bleſs'd you with, I ſhould ſoon alter the condition you ſo little admire; but there is ſuch cunning (as I may truly ſay) on the Female ſide, that a man dares hardly begin; for if he once break his mind, he muſt either proceed to his diſadvantage, or retreat diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with theſe diſingenuous reflections, He loves the Money better than the Woman, he only comes for Money, not for a Wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which made a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y, that it was eaſier to gain a hundred
<pb facs="tcp:179339:36"/> new Miſtreſſes than put off one old one. To marry when a bleſs'd opportunity offers is one part of my reſolution, another is to be on all occaſions,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your faithful Friend and humble Servant, <hi>H. R.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter to perſwade a young Man to mind his Buſineſs.</head>
                     <p>YOU have not many Friends or Relations to truſt to, neither would I wiſh you to be troubleſome to thoſe you have: It is both your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and intereſt to mind your Imployment (which if prudently manag'd) will get you both Friends, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Reputation. There is no Imployment ſo mean but theſe three qualifications, Ability, Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Sobriety will improve to a good account. The firſt you have; the other two if you want it is your own fault. Cuſtom is a ſecond nature, and if you find your ſelf addicted to any ill one, ſtrive to reform, and Cuſtom will be as kind on the better ſide. Some take pleaſure to ſit amongſt idle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, ſpending both money and time in vain. But the worſt is, buſineſs neglected diſobliges our Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and when they conceive ill thoughts of our Conduct, certain ruin follows. Men of buſineſs ought to improve every opportunity to oblige thoſe by whom they live: this trouble is but for a while;
<pb facs="tcp:179339:37"/> for it is time to take our pleaſure when our intereſt will allow. It is a great comfort (and it is looked upon accordingly) for a man to live by his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry without being troubleſome to Friends, a thing grievous to a generous Spirit. This pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and deny your ſelf your humour for a time. If this my advice without deſign I lovingly give be prudently followed, you will in time be ſenſible how much I am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Friend and Servant.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter to diſſwade one from Diſputes about Religion.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Will,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THE eſteem I bear you hath prevail'd with me to warn you of a weakneſs (you ſeem to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge) which if continued will expoſe you to many inconveniences; and this is your readineſs to ingage in controverſies about Opinions, but eſpecially to diſpute points of Religion more paſſionately than conſiſts with good manners. Wary and prudent men ſhun ſuch unpleaſant and unprofitable diſcourſe, which rarely if ever produces any fruit but contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſlike, ſeeing all Diſputants contend more for Victory than Truth. No good man profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth any Religion but believes it the beſt; ſo that he who undertakes to impugn that, does but upbraid him with want of Judgment in ſuch an important choice. And as ſuch attempts are very unmannerly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179339:37"/> ſo they are full of danger, eſpecially if the Opinions be eſtabliſhed by publick Authority; for thereby you take upon you to arraign and condemn the Wiſdom of the Nation, and the Juſtice and Policy of the Government, which will be ever tender of its own Reputation: ſuch Diſputes ought to be made as remarkable for their puniſhment, as they are in themſelves hatefull for their folly. If any will needs thruſt ſuch diſcourſe upon you, it's beſt to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as much indifferency and unconcern as you can, and to propoſe your own ſenſe rather as doubts wherein you deſire to be ſatisfied, than concluſions and fixed reſolutions. Thus, Sir, I have adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to lay before you my weak Judgment in this nice Affair, wherein, if you ſeriouſly reflect, I hope you will find no cauſe to impute it to officiouſneſs or impertinency in,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Affectionate Friend and Well-wiſher, <hi>J. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter to perſwade a Friend to give his Children good Education.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Am heartily glad to hear that your two Boys are ſo hopeful Scholars, pray continue them at School, and give them no other Portions. That
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179339:38"/> good Education is the onely earthly thing here ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, no man will queſtion; It teaches us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Souls, Bodies and Eſtates. Breeding proves often a better and ſurer Eſtate than Lands, Riches and Honour; Theſe are ſubject to loſſes, chances and revolutions; but Learning is an ineſtimable Treaſure which cannot be taken away: what char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges we are at upon that account, is the beſt beſtowed of any. It is no diſgrace (although a great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie) for a Gentleman to be poor, but to be illiterate or rude is a great blot to his Reputation. Education ſupplies all defects both of Birth, Riches and Honour. Amongſt the ſeveral parts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I look upon Writing and Arithmetick not the leaſt; for thoſe who have neglected other Learning, are thereby in little time, and at ſmall charge made capable for any Imployment; the Pen is a certain Refuge when Trades fail; you will rarely ſee any ſober Perſon ſo qualified in want. This I adviſe, not that I think you ignorant of what is proper, but onely for the love I bear to theſe young Gentlemen, which is the duty of,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>London, <date>March 12. 1685/6.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your moſt obliged humble Servant,</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:179339:38"/>
                     <head>A Letter of Advice from a Father to a Son.</head>
                     <p>YOU are now of Age ſufficient (Son) to govern your ſelf, I have diſcharg'd my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty according to my ability; and ſince you are to act for your ſelf in this troubleſome World, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you, firſt, to be religious; ſhew it rather in your Actions than your Words: be alſo loyal to your King; obedience to your Prince is part of your duty towards God. Secondly, Behave your ſelf obligingly to all men, eſpecially your Neighbours both inferiours and equals; diſoblige none willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for one man diſoblig'd will take more pains to be reveng'd, than an hundred perſons, you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, will do to be thankful. Thirdly, Let your Expences be rather within, than either equal to, or above your Eſtate. It's better to have ſufficient to keep up a middle rank, than to be forced to run in debt to maintain a higher. It is a great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to be in debt, but if you muſt, keep your word ſacredly; if you expect Reputation. Fourthly, Shun all Quarrels, Gaming and Law-ſuits, and do every thing with a cheerful Countenance and fair Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Laſtly, Shun evil and extravagant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, uſe honeſt and harmleſs Recreation; the reſt I refer to your own diſcretion. Theſe things well conſidered will be the means of a comfortable life and a happy end; which that you may have, and all good Chriſtians, ſhall be the hearty Prayers of,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your loving Father,</hi> Tr. P.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:39"/>
                  <head>Forms of Bills, Bonds, Acquittances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which ſuch Writings may be made on occaſion.</head>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="bill">
                              <head>A ſhort Bill of Debt. <hi>March 13. 1685/6.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>BOrrowed and Received of <hi>James Lawſon</hi> the Sum of Ten Pounds <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money, which I do hereby promiſe to pay to him or his order upon demand; witneſs my Hand, Day and Year above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Thomas Howard.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="bill">
                              <head>A Bill of Debt.</head>
                              <p>KNow all men by theſe preſents, that I <hi>Henry Compton</hi> of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>James's Weſtminſter,</hi> and County of <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> Gentleman, do ow and am indebted unto <hi>Thomas Stevinſon</hi> of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>Martin's in the Fields,</hi> and County aforeſaid, Scrivener, The Sum of Twenty Pounds of good and lawful Money of <hi>England,</hi> to be paid to the aboveſaid <hi>Thomas Stevinſon,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,
<pb facs="tcp:179339:39"/> in and upon the ſecond day of <hi>June</hi> next enſuing the date hereof, without fraud or farther delay: For the which payment well and truly to be made, I bind me, my Heirs, Executors and Adminiſtrators in the penal Sum of Forty Pounds of like Money of <hi>England,</hi> firmly by theſe Preſents. In witneſs whereof I have hereunto ſet my Hand and Seal the firſt day of <hi>March,</hi> 1685/6.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>Signed, ſealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the preſence of</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>John Templer,</item>
                                       <item>Richard Johnſon.</item>
                                       <item>Henr. Compton.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="obligation">
                              <head>An Obligation with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>NOverint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi per praeſentes me</hi> Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Trant, <hi>de Parochia Sancti</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garetae <hi>de</hi> Weſtm. <hi>&amp; Com.</hi> Midd. <hi>Clericum, Teneri &amp; firmiter obligari</hi> Edwardo Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linſon <hi>de eadem Parochia &amp; Com. Generoſo in Ducent. Libris bonae &amp; legalis Monetae</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, <hi>Solvend. eidem</hi> Edwardo Tomlinſon <hi>aut ſuo certo Attornato Executoribus, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtratoribus vel Aſſignatis ſuis, ad quam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſolutionem bene &amp; fideliter faciendam ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligo me, Haeredes, Executores &amp; Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>s firmiter per praeſentes, Sigillo meo ſigillat. dat. ſexto die</hi> Aprilis, <hi>Anno Regni Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> Jacobi <hi>II. Dei Gratia Magnae</hi> Britanniae, Fran. <hi>&amp;</hi> Hib. <hi>Secundo Anno<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> Dom.</hi> 1686.</p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:179339:40"/>
                              <p>THE Condition of this Obligation is ſuch, That if the above-bounden <hi>John Trant,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators or Aſſigns ſhall well and truly pay or cauſe to be paid to the above-named <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Tomlinſon,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators the full ſum of One hundred pounds, with lawful Intereſt of good and lawful Money of <hi>England,</hi> in and upon the ſeventh day of <hi>July</hi> next enſuing the date hereof, at, or in the Dwelling-houſe of the ſaid <hi>Edward Tomlinſon</hi> without fraud or far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, that then this preſent Obligation ſhall be void, and of no effect, or elſe to remain in full force and virtue.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>Signed, ſealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the preſence of</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>Tho. Manly,</item>
                                       <item>Robert Jacobs.</item>
                                       <item>John Trant.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="obligation">
                              <head>An Obligation in Engliſh.</head>
                              <p>KNow all men by theſe Preſents, that I <hi>Thomas Hunter</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Martins in the Fields,</hi> and County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> Gent. am holden, and firmly do ſtand bound unto <hi>James Howel</hi> of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>James's Weſtminſter,</hi> and County aforeſaid, Grocer, in the Sum of Forty Pound of good and lawful Money
<pb facs="tcp:179339:40"/> of <hi>England,</hi> to be paid unto the ſaid <hi>James Howel,</hi> his certain Attorney, his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Adminiſtrators or Aſſigns whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; to the which payment well and truly to be made, I do hereby bind my ſelf, my Heirs, Executors and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators firmly by theſe Preſents; ſealed with my Seal. Dated the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> in the Second Year of the Reign of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord King <hi>James</hi> the Second, in the Year of our Lord 1686.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="obligation">
                              <head>THE Condition of this Obligation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>Upon payment of all Bonds, Bills, Accounts or Bargains whatſoever, it is proper to take an Acquittance, beſides ſeeing the Account, Bill or Bond cancell'd or croſs'd; and where Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is paid in part, onely make mention, ſo much paid in part of ſuch a Debt, Bill, Bond or Account; but when you pay a man all you ow him, it's very fit to take a general Releaſe or Acquittance.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="acquittance">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>A ſhort Acquittance.</hi> May 1. 1686.</head>
                              <p>REceived then of <hi>Abraham Baldwin</hi> the ſum of Twenty Pounds in full for Goods bought by him of me; I ſay, received in full for Goods and all other Accounts, Debts, Dues and Demands which in Law, Juſtice or Equity I can any ways demand of him preceding the date hereof, witneſs my Hand, Day and Year above-written.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:179339:41"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="release">
                              <head>A General Releaſe.</head>
                              <p>BE it known unto all men by theſe Preſents, That I <hi>William Chalmer</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Martins in the Fields,</hi> and County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> Gent. have remiſed, releaſed and quitclaimed, and by theſe Preſents, do for me, my Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, remiſe, releaſe, and for ever quitclaim unto <hi>Edward Bromley,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, all, and all manner of Actions, Suits, Cauſes and Accounts, Debts, Duties, Reckonings, Sum and Sums of Money, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, Judgments, Executions and Demands whatſoever, which I the ſaid <hi>William Chalmer</hi> ever had, or which I, my Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, or any of us, in time to come, can or may have, to, for, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Edward Bromley,</hi> his Heirs, Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, Adminiſtrators or Aſſigns, for, or by reaſon of any matter, cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap> or thing whatſoever preceding the date hereof. In witneſs whereof I have hereunto put my Hand and Seal the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>July,</hi> in the ſecond Year of the Reign of our Soverain Lord King <hi>James</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and in the Year of our Lord 1686.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>Signed, ſealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the preſence of</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>Jo. Stuart,</item>
                                       <item>Fr. Dalton.</item>
                                       <item>Will. Chalmer.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:41"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:179339:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:46"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179339:46"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
